Hey, thank you guys for joining this session.
이 세션에 참여해 주셔서 감사합니다.
A technical session at 4 p.m. in the afternoon.
오후 4시에 기술 세션이 있습니다.
Hope you guys are ready for that.
다들 준비됐길 바랍니다.
How was the day today?
오늘 하루 어땠어요?
How was the talk?
대화는 어땠어요?
Did you guys have awesome?
재밌었어?
Amazing.
굉장해.
All right, so let me try to close it with like a good note, I guess.
좋아, 그럼 좋은 느낌으로 마무리해보자.
Today we're going to do a workshop on how to build an eBPF, a CNI plugin that uses eBPF.
오늘은 eBPF를 사용하는 CNI 플러그인인 eBPF를 구축하는 방법에 대한 워크샵을 진행하겠습니다.
It's going to be a tutorial for about an hour and a half.
약 한 시간 반 동안 튜토리얼이 진행될 예정입니다.
I'm going to try to make it actually shorter just for you guys to rest a bit from this
여러분들이 잠시 쉴 수 있도록 실제로는 더 짧게 만들려고 합니다.
long day.
긴 하루였어.
All right.
다 됐다.
You guys ready?
준비됐어?
Amazing.
놀랍군.
Let's do it.
해보자.
All right.
됐어요.
A bit by myself, my name is Adam Saya.
조금 혼자서, 제 이름은 아담 사야입니다.
I work at Solo.
저는 솔로에서 일해요.
In the past couple years, I've been very focused on what we call application networking in
지난 몇 년 동안 저는 애플리케이션 네트워킹이라는 분야에 집중해 왔습니다.
general.
일반.
So I deal with API getways and service mesh every day.
그래서 저는 매일 API 겟웨이와 서비스 메시를 처리합니다.
And kind of the focus there is to secure the traffic and secure the network in general.
그리고 트래픽을 보호하고 네트워크를 전반적으로 보호하는 데 중점을 두고 있습니다.
Now one thing I'm very much interested in these days is how can I do more instead of
요즘 제가 가장 관심을 갖고 있는 것은 어떻게 하면 더 많은 일을 할 수 있을까 하는 것입니다.
operating at L7 on the layer seven, where it's kind of the application layer, I want
애플리케이션 레이어에 해당하는 레이어 7의 L7에서 작동하는 것입니다.
to see how many policies and how much we can get from controlling the traffic way earlier
얼마나 많은 정책과 트래픽을 더 일찍 제어할 수 있는지 확인합니다.
on the network stack.
네트워크 스택에서
That's basically where the CNI and eBPF operates, right?
기본적으로 CNI와 eBPF가 작동하는 위치죠?
It's very much networking at a very low level.
아주 낮은 수준에서 네트워킹을 하는 거죠.
So today, again, we are going to do a CNI eBPF workshop, but we are not going to recreate
그래서 오늘도 CNI eBPF 워크숍을 진행하되, 다음과 같은 상황을 재현하지는 않을 것입니다.
Solyan.
솔리안.
We are not going to do something, anything complicated.
우리는 뭔가 복잡한 일을 하지 않을 거야.
I think the goal of this session is mainly to solve this curiosity that everyone has.
이 세션의 목표는 주로 모든 사람이 가지고 있는 이 궁금증을 해결하는 것이라고 생각합니다.
For example, for me, when I was a kid, I always been asking my dad, like, hey, how
예를 들어, 저는 어렸을 때 항상 아빠에게 이렇게 물었습니다.
things work?
작동하는 거야?
And he gave me like the quick pitch, right?
그리고 그는 나에게 빠른 피치를 주었지?
For example, for us today is like opening a car and, you know, open the hood and saying,
예를 들어, 오늘 우리에게는 자동차를 열고 보닛을 열면서 이렇게 말하는 것과 같습니다,
hey, this is the engine and this is the battery.
이봐, 이건 엔진이고 이건 배터리야.
And, you know, that's pretty much it.
여기까지입니다.
As long as if we can understand the kind of the underlying mechanism being used in these
만약 우리가 이것들에 사용되는 기본 메커니즘의 종류를 이해할 수 있다면.
technologies like Solyan and other big project that use eBPF, then it's a good it's a good
솔리안과 같은 기술이나 eBPF를 사용하는 다른 대형 프로젝트에서 사용되는 기본 메커니즘의 종류를 이해할 수만 있다면
day.
All right.
알았어요.
끝났어요.
So let's get started.
그럼 시작하죠.
What we are going to do today, a couple of things.
오늘 우리가 할 일은 몇 가지입니다.
We're going to start with a small presentation around what's a CNI.
먼저 CNI가 무엇인지에 대한 간단한 프레젠테이션으로 시작하겠습니다.
Okay, very few slides going on talking about the basics.
자, 기본에 대해 설명하는 슬라이드가 거의 없습니다.
We're not going to deep dive too much into it, but at least just to get the main idea
너무 깊게 파고들지는 않겠지만, 최소한 주요 아이디어는 얻을 수 있습니다.
of how things work.
어떻게 작동하는지에 대해서요.
After that, we are going to use our laptops.
그 후에는 노트북을 사용할 것입니다.
I don't know if you guys are ready for that.
여러분들이 준비되었는지 모르겠네요.
You guys can follow with me to to create our own first CNI.
여러분은 저와 함께 우리만의 첫 번째 CNI를 만들 수 있습니다.
After that, we're going to talk about eBPF and kind of the use cases we can use it with
그 다음에는 eBPF와 이를 사용할 수 있는 몇 가지 사용 사례에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
the CNI.
CNI.
We are going to talk about a bit of more complexity there when we talk about monitoring.
모니터링에 대해 이야기할 때 조금 더 복잡한 이야기를 하려고 합니다.
And we're going to end with how we can use eBPF for security in our in our CNI.
마지막으로 CNI에서 보안을 위해 eBPF를 사용하는 방법을 살펴보겠습니다.
And at the end, we're just going to have a small conclusion and any questions.
마지막에는 간단한 결론과 질문이 있을 것입니다.
All right.
좋아요.
You guys ready again?
다시 준비됐어?
Awesome.
멋지네.
굉장해.
All right.
좋아.
So a quick question because I was very much when designing this workshop, I was, you know,
이 워크샵을 디자인할 때 정말 궁금한 게 많아서 질문 하나만 할게요,
trying to figure out the right technology to use especially for the code.
특히 코드에 사용할 적절한 기술을 찾으려고 노력했습니다.
So just by a raise of hand here, who writes Golang?
골랑을 쓰는 사람 손들어 보세요.
All right.
알았어요.
Good thing because we're going to do this in bash.
잘됐네, 배쉬에서 이걸 할 거니까.
Right.
그렇군요.
오른쪽
I was looking for the kind of the simplest way to do it.
가장 간단한 방법을 찾고 있었어요.
And I think bash helps a lot.
그리고 배쉬가 많은 도움이 될 것 같아요.
Bash has a lot of abstractions and you can just like use, you know, CLI that are pretty
배쉬는 추상화가 많이 되어 있고 예쁜 CLI를 사용할 수 있습니다.
much simplifying our life.
우리 삶을 훨씬 단순화시켜주죠.
Golang is definitely the language of choice when you try to deal with this situation.
골랑은 이러한 상황을 처리할 때 확실히 선택할 수 있는 언어입니다.
Selium uses it.
셀리움은 그것을 사용합니다.
There's there's good documentation out there.
좋은 문서가 있습니다.
But obviously it brings its own complexity around error handling all these things today.
하지만 오늘날 이 모든 오류를 처리하는 데는 분명 복잡성이 존재합니다.
We don't need that today.
지금은 그럴 필요가 없습니다.
We just need to understand the mechanisms.
메커니즘만 이해하면 돼요.
Okay.
알았어.
All right.
알았어요.
Let's get going here.
이제 가자.
What is a CNI?
CNI란 무엇인가요?
A CNI is basically if you think about any Kubernetes cluster, Docker, other projects
CNI는 기본적으로 모든 쿠버네티스 클러스터, 도커, 기타 프로젝트를 생각하면 된다.
use CNI is a way to provide the wiring provide a wiring for any container.
CNI를 사용하는 것은 모든 컨테이너에 대한 배선 제공을 제공하는 방법이다.
Right.
맞습니다.
In our case here, we're talking about Kubernetes, a pod, right?
여기서는 쿠버네티스, 즉 파드에 대해 이야기하고 있죠?
How can I allow a certain pod to have a certain IP be connected, be able to reach it, be able
어떻게 특정 파드에 특정 IP가 연결되도록 허용하고, 연결할 수 있고, 도달할 수 있고, 도달할 수 있도록 할 수 있을까?
to interact with it.
상호 작용할 수 있다.
That's the core thing around what a CNI is a CNI plugin this in this example.
이것이 이 예제에서 CNI 플러그인이란 무엇인지에 대한 핵심적인 내용입니다.
Now you can think about a CNI plugin as the, you know, a plumber, basically wire like creating
이제 CNI 플러그인을 배관공이 기본적으로 다음과 같은 와이어를 만드는 것과 같다고 생각할 수 있습니다.
the pipes between kind of the network host, the host network and your containers and pods.
일종의 네트워크 호스트, 호스트 네트워크, 컨테이너와 파드 사이의 파이프를 연결한다.
Okay, so that's definitely the easiest way to describe what a CNI is.
자, 이것이 CNI가 무엇인지 설명하는 가장 쉬운 방법이다.
And now we're going to talk about basically the spec a bit.
이제 기본적인 사양에 대해 조금 이야기해 보겠습니다.
Okay, the spec of the CNI project is stable now.
자, 이제 CNI 프로젝트의 스펙은 안정적입니다.
It's been 100 for a while.
100이 된지 꽤 됐네요.
It has a very well documented way of operating.
작동 방식이 매우 잘 문서화되어 있습니다.
It's straightforward.
간단합니다.
And I definitely invite you guys to read this documentation.
이 문서를 꼭 읽어보시길 권합니다.
In this couple slides, we're just gonna go through the basics.
이 두 개의 슬라이드에서는 기본 사항만 살펴보겠습니다.
But again, there is a couple nuances that I would like you guys to go and review after all.
하지만 다시 한 번 말씀드리지만, 몇 가지 미묘한 차이가 있으니 다시 한 번 살펴보시기 바랍니다.
So what does CNI project provide us?
CNI 프로젝트는 우리에게 무엇을 제공하나요?
It provides us three main things.
이 프로젝트는 크게 세 가지를 제공합니다.
First is the specification of what a CNI is and how it should operate.
첫 번째는 CNI가 무엇이며 어떻게 작동해야 하는지에 대한 사양입니다.
It provides us some example implementation that you can just use and reuse.
여러분이 바로 사용하고 재사용할 수 있는 몇 가지 구현 예제를 제공합니다.
And at the end also provide us some libraries to kind of simplify our life.
그리고 마지막에는 삶을 단순화할 수 있는 몇 가지 라이브러리를 제공합니다.
We don't have to reinvent the wheel every single time.
매번 같은 일을 반복할 필요가 없습니다.
Okay.
알았어요.
And obviously today, we are reinventing the wheel just for an educational purpose.
그리고 분명히 오늘날 우리는 교육적인 목적으로 바퀴를 다시 발명하고 있습니다.
Alright, so if we zoom in a bit of how actually things operate, there is a couple steps.
자, 실제로 어떻게 작동하는지 조금 더 자세히 살펴보면 몇 가지 단계가 있습니다.
Okay, so there's always this, what we call a container runtime.
컨테이너 런타임이라고 부르는 것이 항상 있습니다.
You know, when you use different technology, it means different things.
다른 기술을 사용할 때는 다른 것을 의미합니다.
And if you talk about communities, that's probably kubelets.
그리고 커뮤니티에 대해 이야기한다면 아마도 쿠벨렛일 것입니다.
That needs to create, you know, it needs to create a pod, it needs to wire it.
이것은 파드를 만들어야 하고, 그것을 연결해야 합니다.
So the way it works is you have this container runtime that needs to interact with something
그래서 작동 방식은 컨테이너 런타임이 무언가와 상호 작용해야 한다는 것이다.
to wire this pods that got created.
과 상호작용해야 하는 컨테이너 런타임이 있다.
In this case, we are using a CNI plugin for this.
이 경우 CNI 플러그인을 사용하고 있다.
The container runtime is going to do first, it's going to go and read a certain configuration.
컨테이너 런타임이 먼저 할 일은 특정 구성을 읽는 것입니다.
We're going to go into this detail in a bit, right?
이 부분은 잠시 후에 자세히 살펴보도록 하죠?
Right now, we don't have to very much focus on this.
지금은 여기에 크게 집중할 필요가 없습니다.
But now that the CNI runtime, the container runtime, sorry, in this case kubelets for
하지만 이제 CNI 런타임, 컨테이너 런타임, 미안하지만 이 경우 쿠벨렛은
communities, we'll go and look for a network configuration.
커뮤니티로 이동하여 네트워크 구성을 찾아보겠습니다.
Okay, it's a file.
좋아요, 파일입니다.
It's just a JSON file that describes certain things that we need to pass to a CNI.
CNI에 전달해야 하는 특정 사항을 설명하는 JSON 파일입니다.
And then it's going to actually call a binary, just a bin, passing certain environment variables
그리고 실제로 바이너리를 호출하여 특정 환경 변수를 전달합니다.
and that network configuration and expects couple things from that CNI plugin.
그리고 그 네트워크 구성과 CNI 플러그인에서 몇 가지를 기대합니다.
So the CNI plugin is going to receive this configuration, it's going to be invoked with
따라서 CNI 플러그인은 이 구성을 수신하고, 다음과 같이 호출됩니다.
certain environment variables.
특정 환경 변수.
The CNI plugin based on this information is going to do what the CNI plugin is doing,
이 정보를 기반으로 CNI 플러그인은 CNI 플러그인이 수행하는 작업을 수행합니다,
you know, creating the interface, wiring everything, and then returns a result that goes back to
인터페이스를 만들고, 모든 것을 배선하고, 그리고 나서 다시
the container runtime to say, well, this was a success.
로 돌아가는 결과를 컨테이너 런타임에 반환합니다.
My container now is wired.
이제 컨테이너가 연결되었습니다.
Okay, in a nutshell, that's what it is.
네, 간단히 말해서 그렇습니다.
It's basically a configuration file, a binary, and something that calls the binary with this
기본적으로 구성 파일, 바이너리, 그리고 이 바이너리를 호출하는 무언가입니다.
configuration file.
구성 파일입니다.
Okay.
오케이.
All right.
알았어요.
So let's take a look at the configuration file.
이제 구성 파일을 살펴봅시다.
And this is a very simple one.
이것은 매우 간단합니다.
Every CNI configuration file has couple fields.
모든 CNI 구성 파일에는 몇 개의 필드가 있습니다.
Certain are mandatory and certain are optional.
어떤 것은 필수이고 어떤 것은 선택 사항입니다.
Definitely the thing that is very important here is the CNI version.
여기서 가장 중요한 것은 CNI 버전입니다.
Again, I said there is multiple specifications.
다시 말하지만, 여러 가지 사양이 있다고 말씀드렸습니다.
The last one is 100.
마지막은 100입니다.
That's the one we're using today.
이것이 우리가 오늘 사용하는 것입니다.
But there's also other ones like, you know, 300400, like zero, sorry, 040 and 030 and,
하지만 300400, 040, 030 등 다른 숫자도 있습니다,
you know, old versions.
옛날 버전도 있죠
Then there is the type.
그리고 유형이 있습니다.
The type is, in our case, if you want to simplify it, is the binary name that we are going to
유형은, 우리의 경우 단순화하자면, 다음과 같은 바이너리 이름입니다.
invoke, right?
호출하는 거죠?
In this case, it's called bridge.
이 경우 브리지라고 합니다.
Then we have certain keys that are called well-known keys, right?
그렇다면 잘 알려진 키라고 불리는 특정 키가 있지요?
Well-known keys, like in my example here, IPAM and DNS.
여기 예시에서처럼 잘 알려진 키는 IPAM과 DNS입니다.
Well-known keys can be used by CNI to invoke another CNI plugin, right?
잘 알려진 키는 CNI에서 다른 CNI 플러그인을 호출하는 데 사용할 수 있지요?
That's what you call like delegation, for example.
예를 들어 위임과 같은 것을 위임이라고 합니다.
I don't want to go too much in detail about this subject.
이 주제에 대해 너무 자세히 설명하고 싶지 않아요.
We're not going to use it today.
오늘은 사용하지 않겠습니다.
But for example, if you are invoking a CNI plugin that needs to basically assign a certain
그러나 예를 들어, 기본적으로 특정 값을 할당해야 하는 CNI 플러그인을 호출할 때
IP, sometimes you want to use another CNI plugin that is much actually very focused
IP를 할당해야 하는 경우, 다른 CNI 플러그인을 사용하고 싶을 때가 있습니다.
on actually IP generation, right?
실제로 IP 생성에 집중하는 거죠?
It can be host vocal, it can be the ICP, it can be other processes.
호스트 보컬일 수도 있고, ICP일 수도 있고, 다른 프로세스일 수도 있습니다.
But again, that's just a small parenthesis here.
하지만 다시 말하지만, 여기서는 작은 괄호입니다.
And again, there is also this field that's called capabilities.
그리고 역량이라는 필드도 있습니다.
And these capabilities are dynamic fields that are being invoked.
그리고 이러한 기능은 호출되는 동적 필드입니다.
When the container runtime invokes the CNI, it dynamically changes this field with certain
컨테이너 런타임이 CNI를 호출할 때, 이 필드를 동적으로 변경하여 특정
values.
값으로 변경한다.
Again, this is probably too much detail right now.
다시 말하지만, 지금은 너무 자세한 내용일 수 있습니다.
We're not going to use that today, but just to know that exists there.
오늘은 사용하지 않을 것이지만, 저게 존재한다는 것만 알아두세요.
I think the last one, which is important in our example, is that you can pass custom key
이 예제에서 마지막으로 중요한 것은 사용자 정의 키를 전달할 수 있다는 것입니다.
value keys.
값 키입니다.
So it's going to be any detail you want to pass to your CNI plugin.
따라서 CNI 플러그인에 전달할 세부 정보가 될 것입니다.
We're going to use this today in our workshop.
오늘 워크샵에서 이걸 사용할 거예요.
All right.
알았어요.
So now let's talk about, I talked about the configuration file.
이제 구성 파일에 대해 이야기해 보겠습니다.
I said it's a binary.
바이너리라고 했잖아요.
We need to invoke the binary with the configuration file.
구성 파일로 바이너리를 호출해야 합니다.
But I also mentioned that when we have a successful call to the CNI plugin, it returns a certain
하지만 CNI 플러그인에 대한 호출이 성공하면 다음과 같은 특정
result that the container runtime reads and be able to process and obviously update itself.
결과를 반환하여 컨테이너 런타임이 이를 읽고 처리하고 분명히 업데이트할 수 있습니다.
The container runtime probably just print that in stdout.
컨테이너 런타임은 아마도 이 결과를 그냥 stdout으로 출력할 것입니다.
It's kind of a format here in JSON that define the IPs, define the routes.
여기에는 IP를 정의하고 경로를 정의하는 일종의 JSON 형식이 있습니다.
Also that's all part of the CNI spec.
이것도 모두 CNI 사양의 일부입니다.
And we don't have to really much dig into it here today right now, but just know that
지금 당장 여기서 자세히 설명할 필요는 없지만, 다음 사항만 알아두세요.
there is a result.
결과가 있다는 것만 알아두세요.
And the result is in our example here for the bridge is to return the IP that's been
이 예제에서 브리지에 대한 결과는 다음과 같습니다.
assigned to the certain container or a certain pod if we're talking about Kubernetes.
특정 컨테이너 또는 쿠버네티스의 경우 특정 파드에 할당된 IP를 반환합니다.
All right.
알겠습니다.
One last quick step here.
마지막 한 단계만 남았습니다.
Let's talk about execution.
실행에 대해 이야기해 봅시다.
Okay.
알았어요.
So the execution of the CNI plugin is pretty straightforward.
따라서 CNI 플러그인의 실행은 매우 간단합니다.
You have the container runtime.
컨테이너 런타임이 있습니다.
They're going to go and read a certain configuration that is by default put under slash etc cni
이들은 기본적으로 슬래시 등 cni 아래에 있는 특정 구성을 읽을 것입니다.
netd and the name of the configuration.
netd와 설정의 이름.
It's going to read that configuration and then invoke the CNI binary based on that configuration
해당 구성을 읽은 다음 해당 구성을 기반으로 CNI 바이너리를 호출합니다.
that is under by default is under slash optc and I've been in the binary itself.
기본적으로 슬래시 옵션 아래에 있으며 바이너리 자체에 있습니다.
So in this case and it passes again, it's executes and pass certain environment variables.
따라서 이 경우 다시 통과하면 특정 환경 변수를 실행하고 전달합니다.
Okay.
And the environment variables, we're going to see that in a second here.
환경 변수에 대해서는 잠시 후에 살펴보겠습니다.
Kind of just a quick intro to things we're going to use later.
나중에 사용할 기능에 대한 간단한 소개입니다.
Every invocation of the CNI plugin has again, it's invoking the binary and passing environment
CNI 플러그인을 호출할 때마다 다시 바이너리를 호출하고 환경을 전달합니다.
variables.
변수를 전달합니다.
This environment variables are the CNI command.
이 환경 변수는 CNI 명령어입니다.
Are we trying to add the container?
컨테이너를 추가하려고 하나요?
Are we trying to delete the container?
컨테이너를 삭제하려고 하나요?
Just checking if the container is good.
컨테이너가 정상인지 확인하는 중입니다.
Then we're passing a container, the CNI container IDs basically in Kubernetes that's the container
그런 다음 컨테이너를 전달하는데, 기본적으로 쿠버네티스에서 컨테이너인 CNI 컨테이너 ID는 다음과 같다.
ID itself.
ID 자체.
Just a reference to the pod that needs to be set.
설정해야 하는 파드에 대한 참조.
We are passing a CNI netns and we're going to get to this later.
CNI 네트웍을 통과 중이며 나중에 설명하겠습니다.
That's basically to, you know, a way for us to control where this network namespace and
이는 기본적으로 이 네트워크 네임스페이스와
I'm going to talk about network namespace in a second, where the network namespace is
잠시 후에 네트워크 네임스페이스에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
going to be created.
이 생성될 것입니다.
A CNI if name is the interface, like, you know, the network interface that the container
이름이 CNI이면 컨테이너가 사용하는 네트워크 인터페이스와 같은 인터페이스입니다.
runtime is expecting from the CNI to create on a specific container or pod in this case.
런타임이 특정 컨테이너나 파드에 생성할 것으로 예상하는 네트워크 인터페이스다.
The CNI args are all the values that we put in our configuration earlier that can be passed
CNI 인자는 앞서 구성에서 전달할 수 있는 모든 값이다.
down to our CNI.
를 CNI로 전달합니다.
And CNI path is optional here, but again, if basically the CNI is not on a default path,
여기서 CNI 경로는 선택 사항이지만 기본적으로 CNI가 기본 경로에 있지 않은 경우 다시 한 번 확인합니다,
then we have to look for where is the, you know, the binaries.
이면 바이너리가 어디에 있는지 찾아야 합니다.
All right.
알았어요.
One last thing here.
마지막으로 한 가지 더.
CNI's can, you can use multiple CNI's, right?
CNI는 여러 개를 사용할 수 있는 거죠?
You can use multiple CNI's, you have to use only one.
여러 개의 CNI를 사용할 수 있지만 하나만 사용해야 합니다.
So sometimes you have different use cases.
따라서 때때로 다른 사용 사례가 있습니다.
You probably have an interface.
아마 인터페이스가 있을 겁니다.
CNI is basically the one that creates the wiring, that creates the interface itself.
CNI는 기본적으로 배선을 생성하고 인터페이스 자체를 생성하는 것입니다.
But sometimes you have another CNI that just do some sort of tuning or whatever it is,
하지만 때때로 튜닝이나 기타 작업을 수행하는 다른 CNI가 있을 수 있습니다,
right?
맞죠?
And sometimes you want to split this logic into multiple plugins.
때로는 이 로직을 여러 개의 플러그인으로 분할하고 싶을 때가 있습니다.
In our case here, CNI one, you know, let's say CNI two is invoked and you get the previous
여기서의 경우, CNI 1이 호출되고 CNI 2가 호출되어 이전의
result from the execution of CNI one passed to the plugin two and to plugin three.
CNI 1의 실행 결과가 플러그인 2와 플러그인 3으로 전달됩니다.
And again, if you have 10, it's going to operate the same.
다시 말하지만, 10이 있으면 동일하게 작동합니다.
You know, that's kind of a way to say, don't think that the CNI is just a replacement.
CNI가 단순히 대체품이라고 생각하지 말라는 뜻이죠.
You have to like completely replace the CNI you have running.
실행 중인 CNI를 완전히 교체해야 합니다.
Sometimes it's complement, they complement it themselves.
때로는 보완이 되기도 하고, 스스로 보완하기도 합니다.
All right.
알았어.
Time to start our first CNI plugin.
첫 번째 CNI 플러그인을 시작할 시간입니다.
You guys all have like access to a laptop.
여러분 모두 노트북에 접속할 수 있군요.
Again, you guys can follow with me here.
다시 말하지만, 여러분은 여기서 저를 따라오세요.
But if you have a laptop and you want to do this lab, like run it on your own environments,
하지만 노트북이 있고 이 실습을 하고 싶다면 자신의 환경에서 실행해 보세요,
that'd be great.
좋겠네요.
All right.
알았어.
The exercise today, what we are going to do is we are going to create a bridge plugin.
오늘 연습에서는 브리지 플러그인을 만들어 보겠습니다.
This is a very simple example.
아주 간단한 예제입니다.
And again, there is multiple ways of creating a CNI.
다시 말하지만, CNI를 생성하는 방법은 여러 가지가 있습니다.
There is, you know, in terms of like defining an interface, there's a point to point that
인터페이스를 정의하는 것과 같은 측면에서 다음과 같은 점을 지적할 수 있습니다.
like villain, there's multiple ones.
악당처럼 여러 가지가 있죠.
But the simplest one, I think to instead, the basic of CNI is the bridge plugin.
하지만 가장 간단한 것은 CNI의 기본인 브리지 플러그인이라고 생각합니다.
So here's what we're going to do in this session.
이번 세션에서는 이렇게 하겠습니다.
Actually, before I get there, if anyone wants to run this workshop on their laptop, right,
사실, 제가 시작하기 전에 이 워크숍을 노트북에서 실행하고 싶은 사람이 있다면, 맞죠?
go on this link.
이 링크를 클릭하세요.
Okay, I'm going to pause there for a second for everyone to copy it.
좋아요, 모두 복사할 수 있도록 잠시 멈추겠습니다.
It's pretty simple.
아주 간단해요.
It's just bit.ly slash eBPF CNI.
bit.ly 슬래시 eBPF CNI입니다.
Okay, that will take you to our lab environment that we're going to use for the exercise.
이제 실습에 사용할 실험실 환경으로 이동합니다.
Are you guys good?
다들 괜찮아?
Just let me know if you guys all okay.
다들 괜찮은지 알려줘.
Awesome.
멋지네.
Okay, cool.
좋아, 멋지다.
I'm going to go back to let me actually start my environment too.
돌아가서 내 환경도 실제로 시작할 수 있게 해볼게요.
So because it takes about two minutes to be ready.
준비하는데 2분 정도 걸리니까요.
Click on that just in the meantime.
그동안 저걸 클릭하세요.
And if you click on start, you should get on this page here, where it tells you that
그리고 시작을 클릭하면 다음과 같은 페이지가 나타납니다.
the challenges is loading.
챌린지가 로딩 중입니다.
And yeah, let's talk about what we are going to do today.
자, 오늘 할 일에 대해 이야기해 봅시다.
Let's create a bridge CNI plugin.
브리지 CNI 플러그인을 만들어 봅시다.
What we are going to do is define the CNI plugin that first creates a bridge if it's
우리가 할 일은 먼저 브리지를 생성하는 CNI 플러그인을 정의하는 것입니다.
not existing, we're going to call it bridge zero, we're going to assign an IP to the bridge,
존재하지 않는 경우, 이를 브리지 0이라고 부르고 브리지에 IP를 할당합니다,
right?
맞죠?
The bridge is connecting is connected with the, you know, host network.
브리지가 호스트 네트워크와 연결되고 있습니다.
So that's how we get the connectivity to the host.
이렇게 호스트에 연결됩니다.
And then the bridge, we're going to define what we call V8 pairs.
그리고 브리지에서는 V8 쌍이라고 부르는 것을 정의할 것입니다.
One V8 pair is like, you can think like a cord, you know, so basically, you're going
하나의 V8 쌍은 코드처럼 생각하면 됩니다.
to put one end plugged to the bridge, the other end plugged to the container.
한쪽 끝을 다리에 꽂고 다른 쪽 끝을 컨테이너에 꽂는 거죠.
Very simple.
아주 간단해요.
Again, have a bridge connected to the host network, have a V8 pair, one attached to the
다시 말하지만, 호스트 네트워크에 연결된 브리지가 있고, V8 쌍이 있고, 그 중 하나는
bridge, one attached to the container.
브리지에 하나, 컨테이너에 하나 연결합니다.
Again, that's what we're going to do.
다시 말하지만, 이것이 우리가 할 일입니다.
So let's go back to this one.
그럼 다시 이걸로 돌아가 봅시다.
Probably take about a minute here.
여기까지 1분 정도 걸릴 겁니다.
Yeah, so in the meantime, since I have a minute here to talk about things, again, we are going
네, 그동안 제가 잠깐 얘기할 시간이 있으니 다시 한 번 말씀드리죠.
to do everything here today in bash for simplicity, and we're taking a lot of abstractions.
단순화를 위해 오늘 여기서 모든 것을 배쉬로 처리하고, 추상화를 많이 하고 있습니다.
But the good thing is, we are going like if you want to do this for real, like and
하지만 좋은 점은 우리가 이걸 진짜로 하고 싶으면
just use like the right technologies, there is multiple projects.
올바른 기술처럼 사용하면 여러 프로젝트가 있습니다.
For example, there is the Selium eBPF project that has good examples of like how you how
예를 들어, 다음과 같은 좋은 예가 있는 Selium eBPF 프로젝트가 있습니다.
you can define actually, you know, the EPF integration later on.
나중에 실제로 EPF 통합을 정의할 수 있습니다.
There is the container network, you know, networking repo, and it has a lot of good
컨테이너 네트워크가 있고, 네트워킹 저장소가 있고, 많은 좋은 점이 있습니다.
examples.
예제들이 있죠.
If you go here on the plugins that are provided, actually the bridge one we're going to do
제공된 플러그인에서 여기로 이동하면 실제로 우리가 할 브리지 플러그인은 다음과 같습니다.
right now in bash already exists in Golang, and you can just go and copy it right away.
는 이미 골랑에 존재하므로 바로 가서 복사하면 됩니다.
Okay, let's go back here to instruct.
자, 이제 다시 돌아가서 지시해 봅시다.
Sticking about 20 seconds.
20초 정도 붙었습니다.
If anyone has a good joke.
좋은 농담이 있는 사람.
No.
아니요.
Okay.
오케이.
So instruct is pretty easy here.
여기서 인스트럭트는 꽤 쉽습니다.
You don't have you don't have to install anything.
아무것도 설치할 필요가 없습니다.
What we're going to need is basically this tab here is going to have a panel on the left
필요한 것은 기본적으로 여기 이 탭의 왼쪽에 패널이 있는 것입니다.
where we're going to have all the instructions.
여기에 모든 지침이 있습니다.
And then we're going to have a terminal on the sorry, a terminal on the right.
그리고 오른쪽에 터미널이 있고, 왼쪽에 터미널이 있습니다.
And we have all the instruction.
그리고 우리는 모든 지시를 받았습니다.
No way saying the terminal is in the left, sorry, in instruction are on the right.
터미널은 왼쪽에 있고, 명령어는 오른쪽에 있습니다.
And it's probably just a copy paste exercise at this point.
지금은 그냥 복사해서 붙여넣기만 하면 되겠군요.
So quick question here, who has this the environments ready?
잠깐만요, 누가 이 환경을 준비했나요?
Wow, so you guys faster than me here.
와, 저보다 더 빠르시네요.
Okay, well, wait for me, right.
알았어, 잠깐만 기다려봐.
Okay.
알았어.
Keep going.
계속해.
Time soon.
곧 도착합니다.
Do you
guys see the the terminal?
터미널 보여?
Okay, good.
그래, 좋아.
Interesting.
흥미롭군.
I'll give it another try on different tab.
다른 탭에서 다시 시도해볼게요.
Ah, there you go.
여기 있네요.
Okay, just being patient.
좋아, 조금만 더 기다려.
Okay, there you go.
좋아, 됐어.
Let's go.
가자.
Let's start.
시작하자.
So what we're going today to do today is pretty straightforward.
오늘 우리가 할 일은 아주 간단합니다.
We are going to first create a Kubernetes cluster, a single node Kubernetes cluster
먼저 단일 노드 쿠버네티스 클러스터인 쿠버네티스 클러스터를 생성하겠습니다.
that doesn't have anything much.
아무것도 없는 노드입니다.
It doesn't have any CNI.
CNI가 없습니다.
Okay, for that we're going to use kube EDM.
자, 여기서는 kube EDM을 사용하겠습니다.
It's it's, it's very simple Kubernetes cluster here again, basics.
다시 한번 아주 간단한 쿠버네티스 클러스터입니다.
So to use this platform is straightforward.
따라서 이 플랫폼을 사용하는 것은 간단합니다.
Go and click on the command, right?
가서 명령을 클릭하세요.
Click on whatever you want to copy, and then go to the terminal and paste.
복사할 내용을 클릭한 다음 터미널로 이동하여 붙여넣기하세요.
All right, first step is creating a Kubernetes cluster without any CNI installed.
자, 첫 번째 단계는 CNI를 설치하지 않고 쿠버네티스 클러스터를 생성하는 것입니다.
It's taking a couple seconds to get it ready.
준비하는 데 몇 초가 걸립니다.
And once done, now we have a Kubernetes cluster.
완료되면 이제 쿠버네티스 클러스터가 생겼습니다.
I can run the second command here.
여기서 두 번째 명령을 실행할 수 있습니다.
It's just to basically wire, you know, the kube config.
이것은 기본적으로 큐브 구성을 연결하기 위한 것입니다.
So now I can run commands like kubectl get pod.
이제 다음과 같은 명령을 실행할 수 있다.
If I run the kubectl get pod command, you guys can see from back there.
kubectl get pod 명령을 실행하면, 저 뒤에서 볼 수 있다.
Good.
좋아.
All right.
알았어.
So if I run the kubectl command, oops, I see here that I have a couple pods that are running,
그래서 kubectl 명령을 실행하면, 여기에 몇 개의 파드가 실행 중인 것을 볼 수 있다,
but I have two that are pending.
하지만 보류 중인 파드가 두 개 있다.
Right?
그렇죠?
So the core ones, the core Kubernetes pods are started, that's fine.
핵심 쿠버네티스 파드가 시작되었으니 괜찮습니다.
But anything that is need that needs a CNI to operate, it's impending, right?
하지만 작동을 위해 CNI가 필요한 모든 것은 임박한 거죠?
That's because we don't have any CNI installed at this point.
현재로서는 CNI가 설치되지 않았기 때문입니다.
So even if you start any like hell world or, you know, HTTP bin, whatever service,
따라서 지옥의 세계나 HTTP 빈 등 어떤 서비스를 시작해도 마찬가지입니다,
it will not work at this point.
이 시점에서는 작동하지 않습니다.
So let's fix that.
그럼 고쳐봅시다.
Let's actually create our first CNI plugin.
실제로 첫 번째 CNI 플러그인을 만들어 봅시다.
The first step we're going to do here is to copy the skeleton of our CNI plugin.
여기서 할 첫 번째 단계는 CNI 플러그인의 골격을 복사하는 것입니다.
Let's copy it and let's open it on this tab.
복사한 후 이 탭에서 열어 봅시다.
So copy the command, like run the command copy, and then let's go to the editor here.
복사 명령을 실행한 다음 여기 에디터로 이동해 보겠습니다.
Press refresh if you don't see it right away.
바로 보이지 않으면 새로고침을 누르세요.
You know, sometimes it takes a couple times to pop up.
가끔 팝업이 뜨는데 몇 번 걸리기도 해요.
Now that you click on the file and let's just read the first, you know, this is the kind
이제 파일을 클릭하고 첫 번째 파일을 읽어보겠습니다.
of the basics of our CNI plugin.
CNI 플러그인의 기본 사항입니다.
It's just a bash file and it has a couple commands that we need to do.
이 파일에는 우리가 수행해야 할 몇 가지 명령이 들어 있습니다.
So we are reading this environment variable CNI command.
이 환경 변수 CNI 명령을 읽습니다.
Remember, right?
기억하시죠?
The container and time execute the binary and pass certain environment variable.
컨테이너와 시간은 바이너리를 실행하고 특정 환경 변수를 전달합니다.
As part of this environment variable, we have the CNI command.
이 환경 변수의 일부로 CNI 명령이 있습니다.
What we want to do in this case, there's multiple operations.
이 경우 수행하고자 하는 작업은 여러 가지입니다.
Actually I'm missing one here that doesn't really matter.
사실 여기서 하나 빠진 게 있는데, 별로 중요하지 않아요.
But in our case, we want to focus on adding a pod and deleting a pod, right?
하지만 우리의 경우, 우리는 파드를 추가하고 삭제하는 것에 집중하고 싶지 않나요?
So in this case, we have case add, delete, check, and version.
이 경우에는 추가, 삭제, 확인, 버전이 있다.
All right, this is very basic.
자, 아주 기본적인 내용입니다.
Let's keep going here and now let's implement the add function in our CNI plugin.
여기서 계속 진행하여 이제 CNI 플러그인에서 추가 기능을 구현해 보겠습니다.
So the add function is going to do a couple things.
추가 함수는 몇 가지 작업을 수행할 것입니다.
The add function is going to grab, you know, first we're going to get the CRDR of the pod,
add 함수는 먼저 파드의 CRDR을 가져올 것이다,
of the node.
를 가져온다.
Like what kind of IPs are allowed on a certain node?
특정 노드에서 어떤 종류의 IP가 허용되는지 궁금하신가요?
Then we are going to create, again, a bridge like we said.
그런 다음 다시 말씀드린 것처럼 브리지를 만들겠습니다.
And then we're going to create the V8 pair, one plugged to the bridge, one plugged to
그리고 하나는 브리지에 연결하고 다른 하나는 다음에 연결하여 V8 쌍을 만듭니다.
the container, and then we're going to return a certain result saying, well, everything's
컨테이너에 연결한 다음 모든 것이 완료되었다는 특정 결과를 반환할 것입니다.
done, everything's good.
완료, 모든 것이 정상입니다.
So let's run this command here.
이제 이 명령을 실행해 봅시다.
We're going to copy the step two add, going back to the terminal, run this.
2단계 추가를 복사하고 터미널로 돌아가서 이 명령을 실행합니다.
And now if you go to the editor, just again, refresh the page if you don't see the new
이제 편집기로 돌아가서 다시 한 번 페이지를 새로고침합니다.
code.
코드가 표시되지 않으면
And let's go line by line here trying to understand what we did.
이제 우리가 무엇을 했는지 한 줄 한 줄 살펴봅시다.
Again, this is Bash.
다시, 배쉬입니다.
It's very much simplified for a lot of things.
많은 것들이 매우 단순화되었습니다.
Write and go if you want to do it.
하고 싶으면 쓰고 가세요.
The first thing is to, we are going to pass, right, we are going to pass the pod CRDR using
첫 번째는, 우리는 다음을 사용하여 파드 CRDR을 전달할 것이다.
the, remember, the configuration, the JSON configuration.
구성, JSON 구성을 기억하세요.
We are going to pass in that JSON configuration the pod CRDR of the node.
이 JSON 구성에 노드의 파드 CRDR을 전달할 것이다.
So every single node has a pod CRDR.
모든 노드에는 파드 CRDR이 있다.
We're going to pass that to the CNI plugin.
이를 CNI 플러그인에 전달한다.
Then we are going to create a bridge.
그런 다음 브리지를 만들겠습니다.
We are using, again, just CLI commands to do a lot of things.
다시 한 번 CLI 명령어만 사용하여 많은 작업을 수행합니다.
In this case, we are creating a bridge called bridge zero.
이 경우 브리지 0이라는 브리지를 만들고 있습니다.
Sorry, I'm just going to remove this so it's easy to read.
읽기 쉽도록 이 부분을 삭제하겠습니다.
Okay, there you go.
이제 됐어요.
Yeah, so the first step, again, is creating the bridge if it doesn't exist.
네, 첫 번째 단계는 다시 말하지만, 존재하지 않는 다리를 만드는 것입니다.
In this case, it's called bridge zero.
이 경우에는 브리지 0이라고 합니다.
Then we are assigning like a gateway IP and IP itself to the bridge, right?
그러면 게이트웨이 IP와 IP 자체를 브리지에 할당하는 거죠?
So the step here is to assign the IP and then we are going, we need to figure out the IP
그래서 여기서 단계는 IP를 할당하는 것이고, 그 다음에는 IP를 알아내야 합니다.
of a container, right?
컨테이너의 IP를 알아내야 하죠?
Again, this is very, very bad code.
다시 말하지만, 이것은 아주 아주 나쁜 코드입니다.
You don't do that in general, right?
일반적으로는 이렇게 하지 않죠?
Do not go and do a random to figure out what kind of IP we have.
우리가 어떤 종류의 IP를 가지고 있는지 알아내기 위해 무작위로 하지 마세요.
But you probably use the ICP instead and so on.
하지만 대신 ICP를 사용할 수도 있습니다.
In this case, we are running this command to figure out, let's grab an IP.
이 경우, 이 명령을 실행하여 IP를 파악해 보겠습니다.
Let's grab an IP within the CRDR range that we pass in the configuration.
구성에서 전달한 CRDR 범위 내의 IP를 가져와 보겠습니다.
So we are doing a random between two and 255, okay?
2와 255 사이에서 무작위 추출을 하는 거죠?
Basically an IP there.
기본적으로 저기 IP입니다.
We're going to grab this IP, put it in the variable called IP.
이 IP를 가져와서 IP라는 변수에 넣겠습니다.
And again, remember the steps are pretty easy.
다시 한 번, 단계는 매우 간단하다는 것을 기억하세요.
First create the bridge, define an IP for the container, create the V8 pair, plug one
먼저 브리지를 생성하고, 컨테이너의 IP를 정의하고, V8 쌍을 생성하고, 하나를 연결합니다.
in the bridge, plug one in the container.
브리지에서 컨테이너에 연결합니다.
All right, so we did, we did the two first ones.
좋아, 처음 두 개는 해냈어.
We created the bridge and we generated an IP randomly.
브리지를 생성하고 무작위로 IP를 생성했습니다.
The step after that is to basically create the V8 pair.
그 다음 단계는 기본적으로 V8 쌍을 생성하는 것입니다.
To create the V8 pair, we are using IP link add where with the one side of the V8 pair
V8 쌍을 생성하기 위해 V8 쌍의 한 쪽에 IP 링크 추가 위치를 사용합니다.
is the CNI if name that's been passed through the execution of the CNI plugin.
는 CNI 플러그인 실행을 통해 전달된 CNI if 이름입니다.
Again, that's configuration coming from the container runtime.
이 역시 컨테이너 런타임에서 가져온 설정입니다.
And the other end is basically the name of the interface that we are going to create
그리고 다른 쪽 끝은 기본적으로 우리가 생성할 인터페이스의 이름입니다.
for this specific pod.
이 특정 파드에 대해.
This new interface is the one that's going to be plugged to the bridge.
이 새로운 인터페이스는 브리지에 연결될 인터페이스이다.
So here's the V8 pair.
여기 V8 쌍이 있습니다.
Now we have our extension cord, right?
이제 연장 코드가 있죠?
But it's not plugged yet.
하지만 아직 꽂혀 있지 않아요.
We just have that.
방금 찾았습니다.
What we are going to do is to plug one end in the bridge.
이제 한쪽 끝을 다리에 꽂으면 됩니다.
There you go.
됐어요.
IP link set, the end of one of the V8 pairs is now plugged in the bridge zero.
IP 링크가 설정되었고, 이제 V8 쌍 중 하나의 끝이 브리지 0에 연결되었습니다.
Now we have the other end of our extension cord that we need to plug in the container itself.
이제 연장 코드의 다른 쪽 끝을 컨테이너 자체에 연결해야 합니다.
So what we are going to do is to define the network namespace.
이제 우리가 할 일은 네트워크 네임스페이스를 정의하는 것입니다.
To do this, we're going to do a couple of commands here.
이를 위해 여기에 몇 가지 명령을 실행합니다.
But long story short, we are defining our network namespace that we called in, you know,
간단히 말해서, 우리가 호출한 네트워크 네임스페이스를 정의하는 것입니다,
we're just using a link here to container.
여기서는 컨테이너로 연결되는 링크를 사용하고 있습니다.
CNI is going to be slash var run netns slash container, CNI container ID.
CNI는 슬래시 var run netns 슬래시 컨테이너, CNI 컨테이너 ID가 될 것입니다.
That's basically our network namespace being defined.
기본적으로 네트워크 네임스페이스가 정의되었습니다.
Then what we are going to do is to basically go and put that other end of the extension
이제 우리가 할 일은 기본적으로 확장자의 다른 쪽 끝을 넣는 것입니다.
cord within this network namespace that we just defined.
코드의 다른 쪽 끝을 방금 정의한 네트워크 네임스페이스 안에 넣습니다.
Okay?
알겠지?
We're going to plug it there.
저기 연결할게요.
The second thing, we're going to define the IP, right?
두 번째는 IP를 정의하는 거죠?
Important.
중요.
We haven't used the IP yet.
아직 IP를 사용하지 않았습니다.
Right now we're using the IP, the one we generated randomly.
지금은 무작위로 생성한 IP를 사용하고 있습니다.
We are defining that, putting that in our network namespace.
이를 정의하여 네트워크 네임스페이스에 넣습니다.
So we did the two things.
두 가지 작업을 수행했습니다.
Again, we plugged the other end to the container.
다시 다른 쪽 끝을 컨테이너에 연결했습니다.
We defined the IP.
IP를 정의했습니다.
The last thing is to define the default gateway that basically just to carry all the traffic
마지막으로 기본적으로 모든 트래픽을 전달하는 기본 게이트웨이를 정의합니다.
that goes within the network namespace out and that through the default gateway that
네트워크 네임스페이스 내에서 나가는 기본 게이트웨이를 통해
we just defined in the bridge.
로 이동합니다.
That's kind of the way to say this is how you route traffic.
이것이 바로 트래픽을 라우팅하는 방식이라고 할 수 있습니다.
So once we did these steps, right, we did, again, probably repeating myself, but just
이 단계를 수행한 후, 다시 한 번 반복해서 말하지만
to understand the concept, we created the bridge, if not existing.
개념을 이해하기 위해 존재하지 않는다면 다리를 만들었습니다.
We defined an IP.
IP를 정의했습니다.
We created the V8 pair and we plugged the both ends.
V8 쌍을 생성하고 양쪽 끝을 연결했습니다.
Now that, you know, you mean like we mean it's good.
이제, 알다시피, 우리가 좋다는 뜻이죠.
We're done now.
이제 끝났어.
We defined connectivity to our container.
컨테이너에 대한 연결을 정의했습니다.
Let's report this success to our container runtime.
이 성공을 컨테이너 런타임에 보고해 봅시다.
The container runtime now will get a result to say, oh, you know what?
이제 컨테이너 런타임은 다음과 같은 결과를 얻을 것입니다.
That's good.
좋네요.
We are using, obviously, the CNI specification format to return certain results.
분명히 특정 결과를 반환하기 위해 CNI 사양 형식을 사용하고 있습니다.
What we are going to use here is we're going to return the certain information, for example,
여기서 사용할 것은 예를 들어 특정 정보를 반환하는 것입니다,
the IP of this specific, we're going to return this IP of this specific container that we
이 특정 컨테이너의 IP, 이 특정 컨테이너의 IP를 반환할 것입니다.
generated.
생성했습니다.
We're going to return the MAC address and so on, okay, which gateway is being used and
어떤 게이트웨이가 사용 중인지, 어떤 MAC 주소 등을 반환할 것입니다.
so on.
등등.
Again, the CNI spec is very much, very flexible and the way it operates is it's captured.
다시 말하지만, CNI 사양은 매우 유연하며 작동 방식이 캡처됩니다.
You know, we don't even have to return it in a certain way.
특정 방식으로 반환할 필요도 없습니다.
Just print it in stdout.
그냥 출력하면 돼요.
That's all we need to do.
그게 우리가 해야 할 전부입니다.
So we're doing a print right now.
그래서 지금 인쇄를 하고 있습니다.
That's the result that the container runtime will capture and say, hey, well, now that's
이것이 컨테이너 런타임이 캡처한 결과입니다.
a success.
성공입니다.
You see?
봤지?
Very basic.
아주 기본이죠.
Again, this is a very basic container.
다시 말하지만, 이것은 매우 기본적인 컨테이너입니다.
Yeah.
그렇군요.
Good question.
좋은 질문이야.
좋은 질문입니다.
So the question is how we got the POD CRDR and why it's not part of the environment variable.
문제는 POD CRDR을 어떻게 얻었는지, 그리고 왜 환경 변수의 일부가 아닌지입니다.
The POD CRDR, this is not part of the spec, right?
POD CRDR, 이건 사양의 일부가 아니죠?
This is basically the spec defines the way to wire a certain POD.
이것은 기본적으로 특정 POD를 배선하는 방법을 정의하는 사양입니다.
It doesn't do it in the context of Kubernetes.
쿠버네티스 컨텍스트에서는 이 작업을 수행하지 않는다.
The POD CRDR in this case is very much tied to the POD CRDR of a node and that's why we
이 경우의 POD CRDR은 노드의 POD CRDR과 매우 밀접하게 연결되어 있기 때문에
have to pass it through the configuration and not through an environment variable.
를 환경 변수가 아닌 구성을 통해 전달해야 한다.
That's basically the result.
이것이 기본적으로 결과입니다.
Okay?
알겠지?
Awesome.
굉장해.
So good.
너무 좋다.
The last thing we have to do here is to define the DELL, the delete command.
여기서 마지막으로 해야 할 일은 삭제 명령어인 DELL을 정의하는 것입니다.
And you guys are going to see it's very hard, very complicated code to add the deletes.
이제 삭제 기능을 추가하는 코드가 매우 어렵고 복잡하다는 것을 알게 될 것입니다.
So copy the delete code, refresh.
삭제 코드를 복사하고 새로고침하세요.
There you go.
이제 됐어요.
Very complicated code.
매우 복잡한 코드입니다.
Okay.
오케이.
That's all we have to do to delete a network namespace in this case, you know, removing
이 경우 네트워크 네임스페이스를 삭제하기 위해 해야 할 일은 다음과 같습니다.
the POD.
POD를 제거하면 됩니다.
It's just going to go and remove the certain network namespace on that path.
해당 경로의 특정 네트워크 네임스페이스를 제거합니다.
Very simple.
아주 간단합니다.
We don't have to define the check.
수표를 정의할 필요가 없습니다.
The version we're just going to return basically which kind of CNI version we're using in this
여기서 반환할 버전은 기본적으로 어떤 종류의 CNI 버전을 사용하고 있는지를 반환합니다.
case, which kind of spec.
경우, 어떤 사양인지 반환합니다.
In this case, we're using 1.0.0, but this code is compatible with multiple versions.
이 경우 1.0.0을 사용하고 있지만 이 코드는 여러 버전과 호환됩니다.
All the, you know, we're not doing anything complicated, so basically we have very much
알다시피, 우리는 복잡한 작업을 하고 있지 않으므로 기본적으로 우리는 매우 많은
compatibility with everything.
모든 것과 호환됩니다.
Amazing.
놀랍다.
You guys ready to see that in action?
실제로 볼 준비가 되셨나요?
I don't want to see some excitement.
흥분되는 걸 보고 싶지 않아.
All right.
알았어.
Okay.
알았어
So before we get there, let's actually talk about the good point that our friend asked
그 전에 친구가 물어본 좋은 점에 대해 실제로 이야기해 봅시다.
here is basically how to pass this POD CIDR information.
기본적으로 이 POD CIDR 정보를 전달하는 방법은 다음과 같습니다.
In this case, I'm putting that directly here, 10.0.0.24.
이 경우에는 10.0.0.24를 바로 여기에 넣습니다.
Why?
왜?
Just because I also controlled the POD CIDR during the installation itself.
설치하는 동안 POD CIDR도 제어했기 때문입니다.
Right.
맞아요.
I passed the same version, so I kind of guessed what kind of version I need in my CNI.
같은 버전을 통과했으니 CNI에 어떤 버전이 필요한지 어느 정도 짐작이 갑니다.
This is not common.
이런 경우는 흔하지 않습니다.
This is not...
이것은...
In real world, this doesn't work like this.
현실에서는 이렇게 작동하지 않습니다.
In the real world, you will need to create a certain process that goes and read, you
현실 세계에서는 다음과 같은 특정 프로세스를 만들어서 읽어야 합니다.
know, calls the Kube API, get the POD...
알고, Kube API를 호출하고, POD를 가져오고...
You're going to need to do this.
이 작업을 수행해야 합니다.
Look.
보세요.
If I take a look at my node...
내 노드를 보면...
It's very small actually.
사실 아주 작네요.
I think I should zoom in.
확대해야 할 것 같아.
So if I do...
그럼...
Maybe I zoom in more.
더 확대해야겠어.
So if I do K get node, so K for kubectl get node, and take a look at what I have, I have
그래서 내가 K가 노드를 얻고, 그래서 kubectl이 노드를 얻고, 내가 가진 것을 살펴보면 다음과 같다.
only one node.
노드가 하나뿐이다.
Again, it's a single node, Kubernetes cluster in this case.
다시 말하지만, 이 경우에는 단일 노드인 쿠버네티스 클러스터입니다.
And if I take a look and do a dash o yaml, then I'll see, like if I scroll up...
그리고 대시 오얌을 실행해서 보면, 스크롤을 위로 올리면...
There you go.
여기 있네요.
You see?
봤지?
The POD CIDR, that's the one I actually just put statically in my configuration file that
POD CIDR은 실제로 내 구성 파일에 정적으로 넣은 것이다.
I'm going to use as an example.
예시로 사용하겠습니다.
But this process is not like that.
하지만 이 과정은 그렇지 않습니다.
You know, if you want to use a real use case, you want to create a mechanism that goes and
실제 사용 사례를 사용하려면 다음과 같은 메커니즘을 만들어야 합니다.
rediscriminates this API, get this address, put it in the template of the configuration
이 API를 재차별하고, 이 주소를 가져와서 구성의 템플릿에 넣습니다.
file that's going to be set on the host.
파일을 호스트에 설정합니다.
So going back to our example.
예제로 돌아가서
So we have the binary now.
이제 바이너리가 생겼습니다.
We're good there.
이제 됐어요.
We're going to create the configuration file.
구성 파일을 생성하겠습니다.
It's very basic.
아주 기본적인 내용입니다.
You see the configuration file for us, the network configuration?
네트워크 구성 파일이 보이시죠?
Very, very basic.
아주, 아주 기본이죠.
We are just putting the CNI version.
CNI 버전을 넣는 중입니다.
We're going to put the type, which is, again, it's the binary name in our case.
유형을 넣겠습니다. 이 경우에는 다시 바이너리 이름입니다.
And we are putting the POD CIDR that I just showed you right now through Kubernetes.
그리고 쿠버네티스를 통해 방금 보여드린 POD CIDR을 넣습니다.
Right?
그렇죠?
That's it.
그거예요.
All right.
끝났어요.
Let's try it.
해봅시다.
If we run this...
이걸 실행하면...
So in this case, I just created two more PODs.
이 경우, 방금 두 개의 POD를 더 생성했습니다.
Okay, just to demonstrate that this thing is broken still very much.
좋아, 이게 여전히 많이 망가졌다는 것을 보여주기 위해서.
So right now, I have two PODs impending my HTTP bin service or POD here is impending.
지금 내 HTTP 빈 서비스에 두 개의 POD가 임박했거나 여기 POD가 임박했습니다.
The sleep one, two, and this coordinates once.
수면 1, 2와 이 좌표가 한 번 일치합니다.
But basically, yeah, I don't have a CNI yet.
하지만 기본적으로, 네, 아직 CNI가 없습니다.
Let's fix this.
이걸 고치자.
What you have to do is just to copy again, I talked about kind of the default where you
당신이 해야 할 일은 다시 복사하는 것뿐입니다. 나는 일종의 기본값에 대해 이야기했습니다.
need to put the configuration.
구성을 넣어야 합니다.
We're going to put our binary, our bash script we've just created under slash opt cni bin.
바이너리, 즉 방금 만든 bash 스크립트를 슬래시 옵트 cni bin에 넣겠습니다.
And I'm going to put the configuration that we just wrote right now, again, under the
그리고 지금 방금 작성한 구성을 다시 한 번
default slash etc cni netd.
기본 슬래시 등 CNI NETD.
Let's do this.
해봅시다.
Wait for it.
기다려봐.
And then give it a couple seconds.
몇 초만 기다려주세요.
More.
더.
Okay.
오케이.
How long am I going to have to wait here?
여기서 얼마나 더 기다려야 하나요?
I should probably do that.
그래야겠어.
I don't think it's erred.
틀린 것 같지 않아요.
Kind of control all the code here.
여기 모든 코드를 제어하는 것 같네요.
What would I err?
내가 뭘 잘못했지?
Did I?
내가 실수했나?
Wait a second.
잠깐만요.
So what do we have here?
이게 뭐지?
We did the modification of the POD.
POD를 수정했습니다.
Take a look.
보세요.
Cop.
Oh, there you go.
여기 있네요.
What's going on?
무슨 일이야?
Oh, there you go.
여기 있네.
What's going on here?
무슨 일이야?
Do I have like, let's just force the deletion just to kind of force cube.
그냥 강제 삭제를 해버려야 할까요?
What is that?
저게 뭐야?
Get what is that?
저게 뭔지 알아?
After the copy?
복사 다음에?
Yeah, I mean, yeah, the copy.
네, 네, 네, 복사본이요.
I don't know.
모르겠어.
Let's see.
어디 보자.
I'm just going to force the recreation of the PODs.
POD를 강제로 재생성해볼게요.
Pending still.
아직 대기 중입니다.
What's going on?
무슨 일이야?
Sorry, let me double check.
죄송합니다, 다시 확인하겠습니다.
Okay.
알았어요.
Describe.
설명해줘.
Yeah.
예
Oh, okay, okay, okay.
알았어, 알았어, 알았어.
Why this is not...
이게 왜...
I did, I put the, yeah.
내가 했어, 내가 넣었어.
This was int-tainted anyway.
어차피 오염됐어.
That's crazy.
미치겠네.
No, I needed to remove the taint for me to schedule the PODs on the master node.
아니요, 마스터 노드에서 POD를 스케줄링하려면 오염을 제거해야 합니다.
But the taints are not there anymore because it scheduled, actually it scheduled the two
그러나 테인트는 더 이상 존재하지 않습니다.
PODs.
POD.
Where is it going on here?
무슨 일이야?
What's going on?
Let's see, let's see, let's see.
어디 보자, 어디 보자, 어디 보자.
Did I miss something else?
내가 뭘 놓쳤나?
Oops.
이런.
What is that?
저게 뭐지?
The node is not ready?
노드가 준비되지 않았나요?
Oh, yeah.
아, 그렇군요.
Yeah, I mean, the node is not ready because the CNI is not there.
네, CNI가 없어서 노드가 준비되지 않았어요.
Once the CNI is installed, it's going to put it back to ready.
CNI가 설치되면 다시 준비 상태로 돌아갑니다.
Okay, what's happening here?
좋아, 무슨 일이야?
Yeah, I did.
그래, 그랬어.
Okay, look, let's do this.
좋아, 해보자.
So not block on this.
차단하지 마세요.
I'm going to get to that in a second.
잠깐만 기다려봐.
I'm going to go back to do the command quickly, just creating a new environment quick, you
다시 돌아가서 명령을 빠르게 수행하겠습니다. 새 환경을 빠르게 생성합니다.
know, to not be blocked on, like try to debug this live because it's not going to happen.
차단되지 않도록, 예를 들어 이걸 실시간으로 디버깅하려고 하면 안 되니까요.
But question, do you guys have the PODs container running?
근데 질문이 있는데요, POD 컨테이너를 실행하고 있나요?
Okay, that's what matters.
좋아, 그게 중요해.
I did that already.
이미 했어.
Meant to both times.
두 번 모두.
So what we are going to do, I think the way I'm going to do it to kind of simplify this,
그래서 우리가 할 일은, 이걸 좀 더 단순화하기 위해 할 것 같아요,
now that PODs are running and all this, that's awesome.
이제 POD가 실행되고 있으니 정말 멋지네요.
So what I'm going to do this quickly is to create, let's go back to my exercise.
그럼 이제 다시 운동하러 가죠.
I'm just going to start that on here and I'm going to catch up.
여기서부터 시작해서 따라잡을게요.
Don't worry, we'll figure this out.
걱정 마, 우리가 알아서 할게.
I have to dime the, should not debug live, never works.
라이브 디버깅을 하면 안 되는데, 절대 안 돼요.
All right, let's go back to this.
좋아, 이걸로 돌아가자.
Okay, awesome.
좋아, 멋지네.
So again, let me know how many ones have that thing running.
다시 한 번, 몇 대가 작동하는지 알려줘.
All right, that makes me happy.
좋아, 다행이네.
That's all that matters.
그게 중요한 거야.
So what we are going to do next is to talk about the next step from there.
이제부터는 다음 단계에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
So now we have the CNI being installed, the node is ready to take traffic, we have the
이제 CNI가 설치되었고, 노드가 트래픽을 받을 준비가 되었으니, 이제
PODs networking figured out, that's great.
POD의 네트워킹을 알아냈군요, 잘됐네요.
The step from there is, okay, let's talk about EPPF now.
다음 단계는 이제 EPPF에 대해 이야기해 봅시다.
Let's talk about how we can improve certain things using EPPF.
EPPF를 사용하여 특정 사항을 개선할 수 있는 방법에 대해 이야기해 봅시다.
So in our example, we did something very basic.
이 예제에서는 아주 기본적인 작업을 수행했습니다.
We just created the interface.
방금 인터페이스를 만들었습니다.
But what if I want to control this interface to, for example, monitor all the traffic going
하지만 이 인터페이스를 제어하여 예를 들어 다음과 같은 모든 트래픽을 모니터링하고 싶다면 어떻게 해야 할까요?
through, or I want to secure the traffic that goes through that interface, right?
통과하는 모든 트래픽을 모니터링하거나 해당 인터페이스를 통과하는 트래픽을 보호하고 싶을 때 어떻게 해야 할까요?
For this, we're going to use EPPF.
이를 위해 EPPF를 사용하겠습니다.
By raising your hand here, who knows about EPPF in general?
EPPF에 대해 전반적으로 아는 사람 손들어 보세요.
Okay, great, great.
좋아요, 좋아요.
So who wrote an EPPF code before?
그럼 누가 전에 EPPF 코드를 작성했나요?
What's that?
저게 뭐지?
Yes, it's by definition.
네, 정의대로입니다.
Okay, so we have a couple ones.
좋아요, 두 개가 있습니다.
Awesome.
멋지다.
All right.
알았어.
So again, this is going to be very, very, very basic code, EPPF code.
다시 말하지만, 이것은 아주 아주 아주 기본적인 코드, EPPF 코드가 될 것입니다.
So don't be scared.
그러니 겁내지 마세요.
We have to write some code, but it's going to be very, very straightforward.
몇 가지 코드를 작성해야 하지만 아주 간단할 거예요.
So EPPF, what it is.
EPPF가 뭐죠?
We can think about EPPF, I'm probably going to skip this because I think it matters more
EPPF에 대해 생각해볼 수 있겠지만, 더 중요한 게 있다고 생각해서 생략할게요.
to talk about this.
이 얘기를 하려고요.
EPPF is, you can think about it as like a VM within the kernel, where you can run some
EPPF는 커널 내의 가상머신과 같다고 생각하면 된다.
code that is very much, you know, in the sandbox that can do things for you, like it can attach
코드를 실행할 수 있는 샌드박스라고 생각하시면 됩니다.
to certain hooks.
특정 후크에.
So there's hooks for everything.
모든 것을 위한 후크가 있군요.
There's hooks for networking.
네트워킹을 위한 후크가 있습니다.
There's hooks for like file access.
파일 액세스와 같은 후크가 있습니다.
Linux defines a lot of hooks for different things.
리눅스는 여러 가지를 위한 많은 훅을 정의합니다.
And EPPF in our case, and here we're going to talk about networking mostly, we can attach
여기서는 주로 네트워킹에 대해 이야기할 것이고, 우리의 경우 EPPF를 첨부할 수 있습니다.
a certain code, watching for a certain hook, and do something.
특정 코드를 붙이고, 특정 훅을 찾아서 뭔가를 하는 거죠.
That's kind of the three parts of what we can do in EPPF.
이것이 EPPF에서 우리가 할 수 있는 일의 세 가지 부분입니다.
Now the do something can be monitor the traffic, it can be secure the traffic, it can be detect
이제 트래픽을 모니터링하고, 트래픽을 보호하고, 트래픽을 탐지할 수 있습니다.
anomalies, it can be a lot of things like this.
이상 징후 등 여러 가지가 있을 수 있습니다.
So here is an example of, you know, if you look at the stack, there's multiple hooks,
다음은 스택을 보면 여러 개의 후크가 있는 예시입니다,
oops, I'm going to put it on slideshow to go there.
웁스, 슬라이드쇼에 올려서 보여줄게요.
If you look at, there's multiple hooks, you know, there's hooks under the lowest level
보시면, 여러 개의 후크가 있고, 가장 낮은 레벨 아래에 후크가 있습니다.
is XDP.
는 XDP입니다.
Okay, from there, there's hooks that goes to traffic control.
자, 거기서부터 트래픽 제어로 가는 후크가 있습니다.
And there's all the way up some some BPF code that can watch for syscalls.
그리고 그 위쪽에는 시스템 호출을 감시하는 BPF 코드가 있습니다.
Who knows here what's XDP or heard of before?
여기서 XDP가 뭔지 알거나 들어본 사람?
Okay, a couple ones.
좋아요, 몇 개만요.
All right.
알았어.
XDP, you can think about it as way like, it's called Express Data Path.
XDP는 익스프레스 데이터 경로라고 생각하시면 됩니다.
It's an EPPF, you know, it's an EPPF that allows you to basically, like, connect to
EPPF는 기본적으로 다음과 같이 연결할 수 있는 EPPF입니다.
the lowest level level of your network.
네트워크의 가장 낮은 수준입니다.
Okay, very, very low level.
좋아요, 아주 아주 낮은 수준입니다.
The thing because it's low level, it is doesn't have much access to a lot of the data of the
낮은 레벨이기 때문에 많은 데이터에 액세스 할 수 없습니다.
traffic.
트래픽.
But it's very fast.
하지만 매우 빠릅니다.
This is kind of the down the pros and cons.
이게 장단점이네요.
The XDP allows us to do traffic shifting fast, rewriting a full packet, like for example,
XDP를 사용하면 예를 들어 전체 패킷을 재작성하는 등 트래픽 이동을 빠르게 수행할 수 있습니다,
I want to load balance from from different points.
다른 지점에서 부하를 분산하고 싶습니다.
I want to detect anomalies super fast.
이상 징후를 매우 빠르게 감지하고 싶습니다.
I want to restrict traffic very fast.
트래픽을 매우 빠르게 제한하고 싶습니다.
You know, I want to I want to build like, let's say, firewalls or someone.
방화벽 같은 걸 구축하고 싶어요.
XDP is very good for that.
XDP는 그거에 아주 좋아요.
TC is a little bit up the stack.
TC는 스택에서 약간 위쪽에 있습니다.
TCs actually have more data around the packets.
TC는 실제로 패킷 주변에 더 많은 데이터를 가지고 있습니다.
So you can do, you know, packet mingling, we can change ports, we can, you know, change
그래서 패킷 밍글링을 할 수 있고, 포트를 변경할 수 있고, 변경할 수 있습니다.
the queue, we can, there's different things that we can do at the at the TC level.
대기열, TC 레벨에서 할 수 있는 다양한 일들이 있습니다.
If you look at Selium, actually, Selium uses both.
셀리움을 보면, 사실 셀리움은 둘 다 사용합니다.
Selium would use certain parts of the of the system in you know, using TC for control of
셀륨은 시스템의 특정 부분을 사용하는데, TC를 사용하여 다음을 제어합니다.
like probably especially routing on ingress because TC can be routed, routing on egress
예를 들어 TC가 라우팅될 수 있기 때문에 특히 수신 시 라우팅, 송신 시 라우팅과 같이요.
where XDP can only be on ingress.
여기서 XDP는 수신만 가능합니다.
XDP allow you to kind of do you know, load balancing again at low level.
XDP를 사용하면 낮은 수준에서 다시 로드 밸런싱을 할 수 있습니다.
In comparison, if you use Selium using XDP, here, here's a, you know, an interesting diagram
이와 비교하여, XDP를 사용하여 Selium을 사용하는 경우, 여기 흥미로운 다이어그램이 있습니다.
I got from the Selium documentation, where it shows you that if you use Selium with XDP,
셀리움 설명서에서 가져온 것인데, XDP와 함께 셀리움을 사용하면 다음과 같이 표시됩니다,
the amount of free data like free CPU is huge compared to like the basic queue proxy.
기본 큐 프록시와 비교했을 때 무료 CPU와 같은 무료 데이터의 양이 엄청납니다.
That is basically saying that using XDP is way faster, more efficient in term of like
이는 기본적으로 XDP를 사용하는 것이 훨씬 빠르고 효율적이라는 것을 의미합니다.
processing of the traffic.
트래픽을 처리합니다.
So let's go back to my environment fast and see if I can catch up with you guys.
빨리 제 환경으로 돌아가서 여러분을 따라잡을 수 있는지 보겠습니다.
So I'm gonna go here, I'm going to create my, right?
그럼 난 여기로 가서 내 것을 만들어야겠어, 그렇지?
Hopefully this time works.
이번엔 잘 되길 바라.
I'm gonna create my environment.
내 환경을 만들어야겠어.
Taking time here.
시간을 좀 가져요.
Great.
잘했어.
Okay.
오케이.
There you go.
이제 됐어요.
Now I'm gonna connect my, my, my queue config.
이제 내, 내, 내 큐 구성을 연결하겠습니다.
I'm gonna skip straight to the final version, which is Dell.
바로 최종 버전인 Dell으로 넘어가겠습니다.
I'm gonna create my EPPF configuration.
EPPF 구성을 만들겠습니다.
Sorry, my my CNI plugin configuration.
죄송합니다, 제 CNI 플러그인 설정입니다.
I'm gonna deploy certain data, like certain application, and tinted the node for master
특정 애플리케이션과 같은 특정 데이터를 배포하고 노드를 마스터로 틴팅했습니다.
so I can schedule things on it.
그래서 스케줄을 잡을 수 있습니다.
And then I'm gonna move my, I'm gonna move my CNI configuration here.
그리고 내 CNI 구성을 여기로 옮기겠습니다.
There you go.
다 됐어요.
Container creating.
컨테이너 생성 중입니다.
I don't know what I did last time.
지난번에 내가 뭘 했는지 모르겠다.
It didn't work.
성공하지 못했어.
All right.
됐어요.
알았어요.
I don't know, like sometimes you do that thousand times before it works.
글쎄요, 가끔은 수천 번을 해야 되는 것 같아요.
You have to do it in front of people.
사람들 앞에서 해야지.
It breaks, right?
부러지죠?
I guess that's the deal.
그런 것 같네요.
All right.
알았어.
Okay, so all the pods are running.
좋아, 모든 파드가 실행되고 있다.
Amazing.
놀랍군.
So I can go to basically take a look at the configuration.
이제 기본적으로 구성을 살펴볼 수 있습니다.
So yeah, if I do an exact, if I do a curl, I'm getting results from HTTP bin.
네, 정확히 말하면 컬을 실행하면 HTTP 빈에서 결과를 얻습니다.
So basically this sleep pod, this sleep pod, think about as the client and HTTP bin as
그래서 기본적으로 이 슬립 파드, 이 슬립 파드는 클라이언트와 HTTP 빈으로 생각하면 됩니다.
being the server.
서버라고 생각하면 됩니다.
So it's just to simulate client server connectivity.
클라이언트 서버 연결을 시뮬레이션하기 위한 것입니다.
Awesome.
멋지네요.
There you go.
됐어요.
Good.
잘했어.
Let's keep going.
계속 가자.
So let's go back to the slides quickly just to explain what we're going to do in the next
이제 슬라이드로 돌아가서 다음에 할 일을 설명하겠습니다.
step.
단계입니다.
Here's what we're going to do.
다음은 다음과 같습니다.
So we created our bridge plugin also.
그래서 브리지 플러그인도 만들었습니다.
Now what we want to do every time we're going to create the V8 pair and every time we're
이제 V8 쌍을 생성할 때마다 우리가 하고 싶은 일은
going to create the interface in our container, we want to plug in an EBPF code.
컨테이너에 인터페이스를 생성할 때마다 EBPF 코드를 삽입하고 싶습니다.
That's it.
끝났습니다.
That's the goal for this first exercise.
이것이 이번 첫 번째 연습의 목표입니다.
Let's write our first EBPF code.
첫 번째 EBPF 코드를 작성해 봅시다.
Very simple.
아주 간단합니다.
So in our case, again, we're going to attach every single time EBPF at every single interface
우리의 경우, 다시 말하지만 모든 인터페이스에서 매번 EBPF를 첨부할 것입니다.
we create.
생성합니다.
Let's go back to our environment.
우리의 환경으로 돌아가 봅시다.
Let's get started here.
여기서부터 시작하죠.
So let's take a look at a very basic BPF code.
이제 아주 기본적인 BPF 코드를 살펴봅시다.
You can open the editor here and let's go through it.
여기에서 에디터를 열고 살펴봅시다.
In this example, in all this workshop, I'm using XDP.
이 예제에서는 이 모든 워크샵에서 XDP를 사용하고 있습니다.
We could have been using TC because more Selenium related, but I'm XDP too.
셀레늄과 관련된 것이 더 많기 때문에 TC를 사용할 수도 있었지만, 저는 XDP를 사용합니다.
But XDP, the good thing here is that is very simple.
하지만 XDP의 장점은 매우 간단하다는 것입니다.
You can actually go online.
실제로 온라인에 접속할 수 있습니다.
There's a lot of XDP information.
많은 XDP 정보가 있습니다.
There's a lot of tutorials.
튜토리얼이 많이 있습니다.
I can give you links at the end of this workshop to go and learn more about it.
이 워크샵이 끝나면 더 자세히 알아볼 수 있는 링크를 알려드릴게요.
So I think XDP is the right technology to first play with EBPF in the networking space.
그래서 저는 XDP가 네트워킹 공간에서 EBPF를 처음 사용하기에 적합한 기술이라고 생각합니다.
So here's the code that we are going to create.
우리가 만들 코드는 다음과 같습니다.
Ignore the includes that actually we're using this library called libBPF that allows us
인클루드는 무시하고 실제로는 libBPF라는 라이브러리를 사용하여 다음과 같은 코드를 작성합니다.
to write our BPF code.
을 사용하여 BPF 코드를 작성합니다.
But the main thing that we need to be watching for is, so this section, in our case, we are
하지만 우리가 주목해야 할 가장 중요한 것은 이 섹션의 경우 다음과 같습니다.
putting XDP.
XDP를 넣습니다.
The section is defining which kind of hook we are looking for.
이 섹션은 우리가 찾고 있는 후크의 종류를 정의하고 있습니다.
So in this case, the section is saying, well, we are going to trigger this on the XDP hook
이 경우, 섹션은 XDP 훅에서 이것을 트리거할 것이라고 말하고 있습니다.
in our network stack.
에서 트리거합니다.
Then every time we get there, we're going to process this method here called process
그런 다음 매번 여기에 도달할 때마다 process라는 메서드를 처리합니다.
XDP.
You can call it whatever.
아무거나 불러도 됩니다.
It doesn't matter.
상관없어.
The name here doesn't really matter.
여기서 이름은 중요하지 않습니다.
I think the section matters more.
섹션이 더 중요한 것 같아요.
And then every time, again, I talked about the fact that every layer has different, like
그리고 매번 다시 말하지만, 저는 모든 계층이 서로 다르다는 사실에 대해 이야기했습니다.
more information.
더 많은 정보.
And since it's very low level, in XDP, we have access to this structure called XDP-MD.
그리고 매우 낮은 수준이기 때문에 XDP에서는 XDP-MD라는 구조에 접근할 수 있습니다.
So what we are going to do is straightforward.
우리가 할 일은 간단합니다.
The first step is we're going to get the data.
첫 번째 단계는 데이터를 가져오는 것입니다.
So every time the packets go through this V8, every time we capture these packets, we
따라서 패킷이 이 V8을 통과할 때마다, 이 패킷을 캡처할 때마다, 우리는
are going to do a couple of things.
몇 가지 작업을 수행합니다.
So we captured the data, which is the packets.
그래서 우리는 패킷인 데이터를 캡처했습니다.
We're going to capture the beginning and the end.
시작과 끝을 캡처하겠습니다.
Right?
그렇지?
Then we're going to try to parse this data as if it's like an Ethernet, you know, packet.
이제 이 데이터를 이더넷의 패킷처럼 파싱해 보겠습니다.
We're going to make sure that basically the data itself is not bigger than the Ethernet
기본적으로 데이터 자체가 이더넷보다 크지 않은지 확인하겠습니다.
packet.
패킷.
Basically, if that happens, that means that's a bad packet.
기본적으로 이런 일이 발생하면 불량 패킷이라는 뜻입니다.
That's actually something you don't need on your system.
이는 실제로 시스템에서 필요하지 않은 것입니다.
That's the first filtering, basically.
이것이 기본적으로 첫 번째 필터링입니다.
You are filtering bad traffic going through your services.
서비스를 통과하는 악성 트래픽을 필터링하고 있습니다.
That's what we're doing here.
이것이 우리가 여기서 하는 일입니다.
XDP abort, the way in XDP, the way it works, there's codes for everything.
XDP 중단, XDP의 방식, 작동 방식, 모든 것에 대한 코드가 있습니다.
If you return a certain value, it instructs the XDP code or EBPF code to do something.
특정 값을 반환하면 XDP 코드나 EBPF 코드에 무언가를 하도록 지시합니다.
In our case here, XDP abort just, you know, stops.
이 경우 XDP 중단은 그냥 멈춥니다.
Like it doesn't process this code.
이 코드를 처리하지 않는 것처럼.
It's not going to filter out.
필터링되지 않습니다.
It's just going to not run on this particular code.
이 특정 코드에서는 실행되지 않습니다.
Then the second thing is we're going to check actually if this is like an Ethernet, you
두 번째는 이것이 이더넷과 같은지 실제로 확인해 보겠습니다.
know, IPv4 code.
알다시피, IPv4 코드.
Like are we looking for an IPv4 structure?
IPv4 구조를 찾고 있나요?
And for that we're using, you know, we're just checking the proto on our code and saying,
이를 위해 우리는 코드의 프로토타입을 확인하고 다음과 같이 말하고 있습니다,
well, does it match, there's a predefined proto for, you know, value for IPv4 packets.
IPv4 패킷의 값에 대해 미리 정의된 프로토콜이 있습니다.
We're going to check that.
확인해보죠.
Okay, that's good.
좋아, 됐어.
If that's a packet that is IPv4, then, if not IPv4, then just pass.
IPv4 패킷이라면, IPv4가 아니라면 그냥 통과하세요.
XDP pass says it means just like follow, don't do anything, right?
XDP 패스는 그냥 따라가기만 하고 아무것도 하지 말라는 뜻이죠?
We don't need to do anything right now.
지금은 아무것도 할 필요가 없습니다.
Just forward these packets.
그냥 이 패킷들을 전달하세요.
I don't have to deal with it.
처리할 필요 없어.
Now if it's actually an IPv4 packet, then we can get more data.
이제 실제로 IPv4 패킷이라면 더 많은 데이터를 얻을 수 있습니다.
And here we're forwarding to, we're actually going to parse it into an IPv4 structure,
그리고 여기서 우리는 이 패킷을 실제로 IPv4 구조로 파싱할 것입니다,
right?
맞죠?
As part of this IPv4 structure, first we're going to check, hey, is it actually an IPv4
이 IPv4 구조의 일부로, 먼저 이것이 실제로 IPv4인지 확인하겠습니다.
structure here?
구조인가요?
Right?
그렇지?
If it's not, so if the size of it is too big, then, well, again, two, I don't have to run
만약 그렇지 않다면, 그래서 크기가 너무 크다면, 다시, 두 번, 나는 실행할 필요가 없습니다.
XDP in this case, abort.
이 경우 XDP, 중단합니다.
But now, again, if it's actually a valid packet, an IPv4 packet, that we parse it correctly,
하지만 이제 다시 한 번, 실제로 유효한 패킷, 즉 IPv4 패킷이라면 올바르게 파싱합니다,
okay, so now I have access to the source and destination address, all the things that comes
좋아, 이제 소스 및 목적지 주소에 액세스 할 수 있습니다.
with the IPv4 structure.
IPv4 구조로
So what I can do, look, I can print in the kernel, right, that's the thing.
제가 할 수 있는 일은 커널에서 인쇄할 수 있다는 것입니다.
Here we're printing in the kernel this source and the destination address.
여기서는 커널에서 이 소스와 대상 주소를 인쇄하고 있습니다.
We're going to say, hey, I got a packet from this address, and I get this packet is going
이 주소에서 패킷을 받았고, 이 패킷이 다음 주소로 가고 있다고 말할 것입니다.
to this address, and let's print that again on the kernel side.
이 주소로 가는 것을 확인하고 커널 쪽에서 다시 인쇄해 보겠습니다.
And that's it.
이제 끝입니다.
Let's actually run this code.
실제로 이 코드를 실행해 봅시다.
Let's go back to the terminal.
터미널로 돌아가 봅시다.
Let's actually just pull the dependency, which is libbpf in our case, and then let's actually
실제로는 의존성(이 경우 libbpf)을 가져온 다음 실제로
build this binary.
이 바이너리를 빌드합니다.
We're building this binary using clang, which is actually our C builder in this case, it
이 바이너리는 clang을 사용하여 빌드하고 있는데, 이 경우 실제로는 C 빌더입니다.
built it into a BPF code.
BPF 코드로 빌드합니다.
Okay, at this point, we have our first BPF code compiled, we're good.
자, 이제 첫 번째 BPF 코드가 컴파일되었습니다.
Let's actually now use it on our interface.
이제 실제로 인터페이스에서 사용해 봅시다.
To do this, we actually need to load, we have to load a specific BPF program.
이렇게 하려면 실제로 특정 BPF 프로그램을 로드해야 합니다.
The binary that got outputted for the previous command is now loaded under sysfs-bpf-bpf-cni.
이전 명령에 대해 출력된 바이너리가 이제 sysfs-bpf-bpf-cni 아래에 로드됩니다.
Okay, so again, at this point, I have some EPF code that can be used.
자, 이제 다시 이 시점에서 사용할 수 있는 EPF 코드가 생겼습니다.
I haven't done the wiring in my CNI to every time I create an interface, attach this code
인터페이스를 만들 때마다 CNI에서 배선을 하지 않았으므로 다음 코드를 첨부합니다.
to it, not yet.
아직은 아니야.
We're going to do this in this section.
이 섹션에서 이 작업을 수행하겠습니다.
So let's run this command.
이제 이 명령을 실행해 보겠습니다.
Let's get to the editor to take a look at what we did.
편집기로 이동하여 우리가 한 일을 살펴봅시다.
No, sorry, on the editor tab, which is a CNI plugin, do some refresh.
아니요, CNI 플러그인인 편집기 탭에서 새로 고침을 수행하세요.
It's the exact same code as earlier.
이전과 똑같은 코드입니다.
The only difference is here is after I actually output my result, I'm saying, okay, everything
여기서 유일한 차이점은 실제로 결과를 출력한 후, 다음과 같이 말합니다.
is good.
좋네요.
Well, actually, wait a second, before we finish this, let's actually attach this BPF code
잠깐만요, 이 작업을 완료하기 전에 실제로 이 BPF 코드를 첨부해 봅시다.
that I just loaded.
방금 로드한
We are using BPF tool net attach xdp on the interface we just created.
방금 만든 인터페이스에서 BPF 도구 net attach xdp를 사용하고 있습니다.
This command here is basically saying run this xdp code on every packet that goes through
이 명령은 기본적으로 다음 패킷을 통과하는 모든 패킷에 대해 이 xdp 코드를 실행하라는 것입니다.
this interface, the network interface we created for the networking in our pod.
이 인터페이스는 우리가 파드에서 네트워킹을 위해 만든 네트워크 인터페이스입니다.
Again, it seems maybe complicated, but it's very straightforward.
다시 말하지만, 복잡해 보이지만 매우 간단합니다.
We wrote some code, we built it, we loaded it, and then we attached it to a specific
코드를 작성하고, 빌드하고, 로드한 다음, 이 코드를 특정
interface.
인터페이스에 연결합니다.
In this case, I'm using BPF tool for this.
이 경우에는 BPF 도구를 사용하고 있습니다.
But again, if you want to do this in a real scenario, and for example, Selium, the way
그러나 다시 말하지만, 실제 시나리오(예: Selium)에서 이 작업을 수행하려는 경우
they do it in other projects, there's different loaders, there's actually some code, you can
다른 프로젝트에서 이 작업을 수행하고 다른 로더가 있고 실제로 일부 코드가 있습니다.
write it in Go, for example, that grabs, you know, they're going to grab this BPF code
예를 들어 Go로 작성하면 이 BPF 코드를 가져올 수 있습니다.
and attach it to a certain interface, you know, in Go instead of like using a CLI like
같은 CLI를 사용하는 대신 Go에서 특정 인터페이스에 연결합니다.
I'm doing.
하고 있습니다.
CLI here is just for simplifying things.
여기서 CLI는 작업을 단순화하기 위한 것입니다.
Awesome.
멋지네요.
So now I modified my CNI code.
이제 CNI 코드를 수정했습니다.
That's great.
잘됐네요.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to, yes, I'm going to basically update, you know, I'm
그래서 제가 할 일은, 예, 기본적으로 업데이트 할 것입니다.
moving this CNI code to OPT CNI bin again, when we have the CNI previously, some override
이 CNI 코드를 OPT CNI 빈으로 다시 옮기면 이전에 CNI가 있을 때 일부 오버라이드는
writing the old code.
이전 코드를 작성합니다.
And let's just delete the pod.
그리고 파드를 삭제한다.
We're going to delete the pod just to force the recreation of the new network interfaces,
새로운 네트워크 인터페이스를 강제로 재생성하기 위해 파드를 삭제한다,
the new pods with this CNI code, CNI plugin code attached to it.
이 CNI 코드, CNI 플러그인 코드가 첨부된 새 파드를 생성한다.
So okay, my two pods are now up and running, which is awesome.
이제 두 개의 파드가 실행 중이며, 정말 멋지다.
So if I run, let's say I'm going to run some traffic.
이제 실행하면, 트래픽이 좀 발생한다고 가정해 봅시다.
There you go.
됐어요.
So I'm making a curl.
컬을 만들고 있어요.
What do you guys think would happen now?
이제 어떻게 될 것 같아?
Now that I run the code, the package went through the V8, my XDP code got executed,
이제 코드를 실행했더니 패키지가 V8을 통과해서 내 XDP 코드가 실행되었습니다,
and I should have logs now in the kernel that shows that this packet got processed.
이제 커널에 이 패킷이 처리되었음을 보여주는 로그가 있어야 합니다.
Let's take a look.
한번 살펴봅시다.
We are reading the kernel logs.
커널 로그를 읽고 있습니다.
There you go.
여기까지입니다.
We see curl got packaged from something to something.
컬이 무언가에서 무언가로 패키징된 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
Okay, there you go.
이제 됐어요.
Our first eBPF code, it just printed something, it just got automatically using our CNI, we
우리의 첫 번째 eBPF 코드, 방금 무언가를 인쇄했습니다. CNI를 사용하여 자동으로 가져옵니다.
not only created all the networking things, all the networking components for the plugin
모든 네트워킹을 만들었을 뿐만 아니라 플러그인을 위한 모든 네트워킹 구성 요소를 만들었습니다.
for, sorry, for the pod to be wired correctly, so we can interact with it.
파드와 상호 작용할 수 있도록 올바르게 연결해야 한다.
But we also loaded an XDP code for us to do stuff on it, right?
하지만 우리가 뭔가를 할 수 있도록 XDP 코드도 로드했죠?
We haven't done yet nothing, we just logged some of the source and the destination address,
아직 아무 것도 하지 않았고, 소스 주소와 목적지 주소를 일부 기록했을 뿐입니다,
but now let's do some interesting things.
하지만 이제 흥미로운 일을 해봅시다.
All right, so the next section, the next exercise is to use eBPF for different scenarios.
자, 다음 섹션에서는 다양한 시나리오에 대해 eBPF를 사용해 보겠습니다.
eBPF, again, can be used for multiple things.
다시 한 번 말씀드리지만, eBPF는 여러 가지 용도로 사용할 수 있습니다.
The main three things that we can think about in networking is eBPF can be used for monitoring,
네트워킹에서 생각할 수 있는 세 가지 주요 사항은 eBPF가 모니터링에 사용될 수 있다는 것입니다,
so you can have metrics and stats around your traffic.
트래픽에 대한 지표와 통계를 얻을 수 있습니다.
It can be used for security, so to block calls that you don't want or traffic from A to B
보안을 위해 원치 않는 통화나 A에서 B로의 트래픽을 차단하는 데 사용할 수 있습니다.
without interrupting basically packets that are not meant to be sent from A to B, for
기본적으로 A에서 B로 보내지 말아야 할 패킷을 방해하지 않고
example.
예시.
The third aspect, or rate limiting actually, or a lot of controls basically can do in security.
세 번째 측면, 즉 실제로 속도를 제한하는 것은 보안에서 기본적으로 할 수 있는 많은 제어입니다.
The third aspect is routing.
세 번째 측면은 라우팅입니다.
Routing, for example, in Selium, I showed you the data earlier, Selium uses it as a
라우팅은 예를 들어, 앞서 데이터를 보여드린 셀리움에서, 셀리움은 이를
replacement of kube-proxy.
kube-proxy로 대체합니다.
You don't need actually to use IPVS or IP tables for routing.
라우팅을 위해 실제로 IPVS나 IP 테이블을 사용할 필요는 없다.
IP tables being, they got created for firewalling, not actually for traffic routing.
IP 테이블은 방화벽을 위해 만들어진 것이지 트래픽 라우팅을 위해 만들어진 것이 아니기 때문입니다.
You can use eBPF and XDP in this case to get way faster traffic routing.
이 경우 eBPF와 XDP를 사용하면 훨씬 빠른 트래픽 라우팅을 얻을 수 있습니다.
In our example in today's workshop, we're going to probably focus on the two things,
오늘 워크숍의 예제에서는 이 두 가지에 중점을 두겠습니다,
monitoring and we're going to focus on security, like a small example.
모니터링과 작은 예제처럼 보안에 초점을 맞출 것입니다.
So before we start talking about, before we start talking about monitoring in details,
모니터링에 대해 자세히 이야기하기 전에, 먼저 보안에 대해 이야기하겠습니다,
actually something we haven't talked about yet is the, you know, I talked about eBPF
사실 우리가 아직 이야기하지 않은 것은, 제가 말씀드린 eBPF입니다.
running in the sandbox in the kernel code, but you cannot get data out of that.
커널 코드의 샌드박스에서 실행되지만 거기서 데이터를 가져올 수 없다는 것입니다.
You know, kernel is basically an isolation in our system.
커널은 기본적으로 우리 시스템에서 격리되어 있습니다.
There's no way to interact directly to get metrics or whatever.
메트릭 등을 얻기 위해 직접 상호작용할 수 있는 방법이 없습니다.
In our user space, user space is basically everything you run on your node, everything
사용자 공간에서 사용자 공간은 기본적으로 노드에서 실행하는 모든 것, 모든 것을 의미합니다.
you create, that's user space.
생성하는 모든 것이 사용자 공간입니다.
Now a user space program cannot interact directly with the kernel space program.
이제 사용자 공간 프로그램은 커널 공간 프로그램과 직접 상호작용할 수 없습니다.
The way they interact and interchange data is to use what we call a BPF map.
이 둘이 상호작용하고 데이터를 교환하는 방식은 BPF 맵이라고 부르는 것을 사용하는 것입니다.
A BPF map, like it says here, it's just a map, a certain type of map.
BPF 맵은 여기에 나와 있듯이 그냥 지도, 특정 유형의 지도일 뿐입니다.
You can do like a ring buffer for streaming data.
스트리밍 데이터를 위한 링 버퍼처럼 사용할 수 있습니다.
You can do hash maps for key value storage.
키 값 저장을 위해 해시 맵을 사용할 수 있습니다.
You can do arrays for just like saving a random number of things.
임의의 숫자를 저장하는 것처럼 배열을 할 수 있습니다.
Basically you define a map and then now the kernel space, the eBPF program that we wrote
기본적으로 맵을 정의하고 이제 커널 공간, 우리가 작성한 eBPF 프로그램을 정의합니다.
can write to that, can write to that map and actually the user space program can also write
에 쓸 수 있고, 그 맵에 쓸 수 있고, 실제로 사용자 공간 프로그램도 쓸 수 있습니다.
to that map, read write in both directions.
에 양방향으로 읽을 수 있습니다.
The user space program can read and write to the map and same thing for the kernel space
사용자 공간 프로그램은 맵을 읽고 쓸 수 있으며 커널 공간에 대해서도 마찬가지입니다.
program.
프로그램.
So what we are going to do in the next exercise?
다음 연습에서는 무엇을 할까요?
We created already our BPF code.
이미 BPF 코드를 만들었습니다.
We just demoed a log to the kernel.
방금 커널에 대한 로그를 데모했습니다.
Now let's do something a bit more interesting.
이제 좀 더 흥미로운 것을 해봅시다.
What we are going to do is a couple steps.
몇 단계만 거치면 됩니다.
We are going to capture the traffic.
트래픽을 캡처하겠습니다.
I mean we did that earlier, same thing.
아까도 똑같이 했잖아요.
We are going to basically write the number of packets that we receive from a certain
우리는 기본적으로 특정 패킷으로부터 받는 패킷의 수를 기록할 것입니다.
source in the map.
소스로부터 받은 패킷 수입니다.
We are going to create basically a map first before all that but then we are going to create
그 전에 기본적으로 맵을 먼저 생성한 다음 다음을 생성하겠습니다.
the number of packets we receive from a certain source in a map and then we are going to use
맵에서 특정 소스로부터 수신하는 패킷의 수를 계산한 다음
what we call user space program to go and read a certain map and expose that as metrics
사용자 공간 프로그램이라고 부르는 것을 사용하여 특정 지도를 읽고 이를 메트릭으로 노출합니다.
that we can see in Prometheus.
프로메테우스에서 볼 수 있습니다.
That is basically full cycle around monitoring and all that needs to be loaded using our
이것은 기본적으로 모니터링과 관련된 전체 사이클이며, 우리의
CNI.
So let's go.
그럼 가자.
Let's do it.
해보자.
So the first step here, click on next.
첫 번째 단계는 다음을 클릭하세요.
All right.
알았어요.
Man, who is tired here?
이봐, 누가 피곤해?
I mean 5.30 in the afternoon I get you.
내 말은 오후 5시 반에 데리러 갈게.
All right.
알았어.
So let's create the map.
그럼 지도를 만들어 봅시다.
The map is pretty straightforward.
지도는 꽤 간단합니다.
What we have to do is define a structure in a certain way, define the values we need
우리가 해야 할 일은 특정 방식으로 구조를 정의하고 필요한 값을 정의하는 것입니다.
to store in and label it a certain way and that basically what creates a map.
저장하고 특정 방식으로 레이블을 지정하면 기본적으로 맵이 만들어집니다.
So in our case here, we go back to the editor, take a look at the code.
여기서는 편집기로 돌아가서 코드를 살펴봅니다.
There you go.
여기까지입니다.
This is the new code of basically the monitoring.
이것은 기본적으로 모니터링의 새로운 코드입니다.
So what we do first is defining the structure that is basically defining the key value and
그래서 우리가 먼저 하는 일은 기본적으로 키 값을 정의하는 구조를 정의하고
we give it a name.
이름을 지정합니다.
We call that counter.
우리는 그것을 카운터라고 부릅니다.
That's our map name.
이것이 우리 지도 이름입니다.
It's called counter, okay?
카운터라고 해요.
We define that is basically storing a key size of U32 and a value size of U64.
기본적으로 키 크기 U32와 값 크기 U64를 저장하는 것으로 정의합니다.
That's it.
끝입니다.
Think about it as a hash map, has a key value pair where the key is a certain size, the
해시 맵이라고 생각하면, 키가 특정 크기인 키 값 쌍이 있습니다.
value is a certain size.
값은 특정 크기입니다.
Very simple.
아주 간단합니다.
Now same thing as all our code from earlier, so we don't really care about this.
이제 앞서의 모든 코드와 동일하므로 크게 신경 쓰지 않아도 됩니다.
The only thing actually we care about is after now at this point since we actually have the
실제로 우리가 신경 쓰는 것은 지금 이 시점 이후입니다.
source address of packets, let's put that in the value and call that source IP key.
패킷의 소스 주소가 있으므로 이를 값에 넣고 해당 소스 IP 키를 호출해 보겠습니다.
So the key is the source of a certain packet, so the IP address of a certain packet.
키는 특정 패킷의 소스이므로 특정 패킷의 IP 주소입니다.
Every time we basically are going to run this method here that comes with libBPF, again
여기서 기본적으로 libBPF와 함께 제공되는 이 메서드를 실행할 때마다 다시 한 번
I'm using this library called libBPF, they're going to give us access to the map so you
저는 libBPF라는 라이브러리를 사용하고 있는데, 이 라이브러리는 우리에게 지도에 대한 접근 권한을 줄 것입니다.
can just call the BPF map and look for the key.
BPF 맵을 호출하고 키를 찾을 수 있습니다.
If this key which is the source address exists, just increment it.
소스 주소인 이 키가 존재하면 이 키를 증가시키면 됩니다.
Just say, okay, well I got one more packet, another packet.
알았어, 패킷이 하나 더 왔어, 또 패킷이 왔어.
Every time I see the key, increment the value.
키가 보일 때마다 값을 증가시켜.
If it doesn't actually exist, well just say, hey, I received my first packet.
실제로 존재하지 않는다면, 그냥 첫 번째 패킷을 받았다고 말하세요.
Again, if-else, very basic here.
다시 말하지만, 만약-그렇지 않다면, 아주 기본입니다.
And then we do return XDP pass which means forward this packet, let it go, let it continue
그리고 나서 이 패킷을 전달하고, 보내주고, 계속 보내주는 것을 의미하는 XDP 패스를 반환합니다.
on the networking here.
여기 네트워킹에서.
So we're going to do the same exact step we did earlier.
이제 앞에서 했던 것과 똑같은 단계를 수행하겠습니다.
So we're going to build our BPF code and then we loaded it again.
BPF 코드를 빌드한 다음 다시 로드합니다.
So we kind of did a reload here.
여기서 다시 로드했습니다.
And we don't have to modify our CNI because it's actually pointing the same value, slash
그리고 CNI는 실제로 동일한 값인 슬래시를 가리키고 있기 때문에 수정할 필요가 없습니다.
sys fs BPF eBPF CNI.
All right, so let's delete the pods just for us to force them to restart with this
좋아, 이제 파드를 삭제하여 다음과 같이 강제로 재시작해 보자.
new code we just created.
방금 생성한 새 코드.
Take about a second here to create the new pods for us and we're going to see what happens.
여기서 잠시 시간을 내어 새 파드를 생성하고 어떤 일이 일어나는지 살펴보겠습니다.
All right, so the two pods being recreated, now let's send a packet, let's send some traffic.
자, 두 개의 파드가 다시 생성되었으니 이제 패킷을 보내서 트래픽을 전송해 봅시다.
So we're going to do a curl call from the sleep pod to the HTTP bin pod.
이제 슬립 파드에서 HTTP 빈 파드로 컬 호출을 할 것입니다.
There you go, I'm getting some results.
이제 결과가 나옵니다.
I can run this a couple of times, it doesn't really matter.
몇 번 실행해도 상관없어요.
Oops, I actually deleted my pods but yeah, I have to, oops, where's my curl?
웁스, 사실 내 포드를 삭제했는데 그래야겠어, 웁스, 내 컬은 어디 있지?
Yeah, so let's do this.
그래, 그럼 해보자.
All right.
알았어요.
I'm getting some returns.
반송이 좀 있습니다.
Now if I use this BPF tool map that's going to dump the values under the counter, again
이제 카운터 아래에 값을 덤프하는 이 BPF 도구 맵을 사용하면 다음과 같이 다시 나타납니다.
I created the map, I called it counter, okay, so it's automatically now loaded.
맵을 만들고 카운터라고 이름을 붙였으니 이제 자동으로 로드됩니다.
If I run this command, there you go.
이 명령을 실행하면 됩니다.
I see now two elements, two values in my BPF map.
이제 BPF 맵에 두 개의 요소, 두 개의 값이 표시됩니다.
So every time I'm running some traffic within my V8 pair, now a certain value is getting
따라서 내 V8 쌍 내에서 트래픽을 실행할 때마다 이제 특정 값이
incremented in my counter.
내 카운터에서 증가합니다.
You saw the power here?
여기서 힘을 보셨나요?
Basically we did pretty much nothing to get certain metrics out of eBPF.
기본적으로 우리는 eBPF에서 특정 지표를 얻기 위해 거의 아무것도 하지 않았습니다.
Actually now let's use what we call a user space program.
이제 사용자 공간 프로그램이라고 부르는 것을 사용해 보겠습니다.
User space program again is a way for us to interact with eBPF.
사용자 공간 프로그램은 우리가 eBPF와 상호작용할 수 있는 방법입니다.
We are going to use this cool project I found online called eBPF exporter, right?
온라인에서 찾은 멋진 프로젝트인 eBPF 익스포터를 사용할 거죠?
It's on GitHub.
깃허브에 있어요.
It allows us to automatically go and read an eBPF map.
자동으로 eBPF 지도를 읽을 수 있습니다.
We don't have to write any code.
코드를 작성할 필요가 없습니다.
So this is running.
실행 중입니다.
So if I do this curl localhost, there you go.
이제 로컬호스트를 컬하면 끝입니다.
See that?
보이시죠?
Now automatically now I have Prometheus metrics that is representing the BPF code, the BPF
이제 자동으로 BPF 코드를 나타내는 Prometheus 메트릭이 생겼습니다.
metrics as Prometheus metrics.
메트릭이 프로메테우스 메트릭으로 표시됩니다.
And actually I can even use Prometheus here to capture that.
실제로 여기서도 Prometheus를 사용하여 이를 캡처할 수 있습니다.
There you go.
여기 있네요.
If I restart Prometheus, now if I go to Prometheus, right?
프로메테우스를 다시 시작하면 이제 프로메테우스로 갈 수 있죠?
Let's take a look at what we have.
우리가 가진 것을 살펴봅시다.
Now we can do, let's see, counter.
이제 카운터를 해봅시다.
See what we have here.
여기 뭐가 있는지 보세요.
I think it's called.
호출된 것 같아요.
Do you see it?
보여요?
Oh.
오
Did I put the metric name here?
내가 여기에 메트릭 이름을 넣었나요?
Oh.
오
Oh, OK.
오, 알았어.
I do things right sometimes.
난 때때로 옳은 일을 한다.
I just don't realize.
나는 단지 깨닫지 못할 뿐이다.
It just, OK, great.
그냥, 알았어.
So you see here we have the two metrics coming back in awesome.
두 가지 메트릭이 멋지게 돌아온 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
So here if you do like in there, I don't know, like five minutes and take a look.
여기서 5분 정도만 시간을 내서 살펴보세요.
Look.
봐봐.
You see that?
저거 보여?
We built a CNI plugin and we built some eBPF code that go and count packets, automatically
우리는 CNI 플러그인을 만들었고 패킷을 자동으로 계산하는 eBPF 코드를 만들었습니다.
load that and now we can see that in Prometheus.
로드하면 이제 Prometheus에서 확인할 수 있습니다.
We did that in, you know, let's say session.
세션에서 이 작업을 수행했습니다.
So basically on eBPF, with eBPF we can do things very low level, super fast.
기본적으로 eBPF를 사용하면 매우 낮은 수준의 작업을 매우 빠르게 수행할 수 있습니다.
You can think about that.
그렇게 생각할 수 있습니다.
Think about things you can do here.
여기서 할 수 있는 일을 생각해 보세요.
OK, here was a very basic example, but now you can write the C code to do probably anything
아주 기본적인 예제였지만, 이제 C 코드를 작성해 다음과 같은 작업을 수행할 수 있습니다.
you want with the packets.
패킷으로 원하는 모든 것을 할 수 있습니다.
And talking about anything we want, let's talk about the next example.
우리가 원하는 것에 대해 이야기하면서 다음 예제에 대해 이야기해 봅시다.
So we talk about monitoring.
이제 모니터링에 대해 이야기해 봅시다.
Let's see what we can do next.
다음에 무엇을 할 수 있는지 봅시다.
And what we can do next is basically security.
다음으로 할 수 있는 것은 기본적으로 보안입니다.
Right?
그렇죠?
So who here used network policies?
여기 누가 네트워크 정책을 사용했나요?
Pretty much a lot of people.
꽤 많은 사람들이요.
All right.
알았어.
Network policies is a fundamental component of, you know, networking in communities.
네트워크 정책은 커뮤니티 네트워킹의 기본 요소입니다.
It allows us to deny traffic from A to B and do a lot of fine tuning, defining multi-tenancy
네트워크 정책을 통해 A에서 B로의 트래픽을 거부하고, 멀티 테넌시를 정의하는 등 다양한 미세 조정을 수행할 수 있습니다.
and all of the things.
그리고 모든 것들.
Network policies, if you want to use eBPF for that, you probably would use something
네트워크 정책, 이를 위해 eBPF를 사용하려면 아마도 다음과 같은 것을 사용할 것입니다.
similar to what I'm showing you right now.
지금 보여드리는 것과 비슷합니다.
If you want to implement that, let's say from scratch.
이를 구현하고 싶다면 처음부터 구현해 봅시다.
And again, this is a very, very basic scenario.
다시 말하지만, 이것은 아주 아주 기본적인 시나리오입니다.
So what we are going to do for the next example is pretty straightforward.
다음 예제에서 할 일은 매우 간단합니다.
We are going to first create, we're going to create our network policy in communities.
먼저 커뮤니티에서 네트워크 정책을 만들겠습니다.
Okay?
알았지?
Just a super basic one, simple, just for demo.
데모용으로 아주 기본적인 것만 만들었습니다.
We're going to create a user space program to kind of read this network policy and actually
이 네트워크 정책을 읽을 수 있는 사용자 공간 프로그램을 만들어서 실제로
go and create certain rules in like our BPF map.
BPF 맵과 같은 특정 규칙을 생성합니다.
Then our eBPF code on the kernel side is going to read these rules from the map and
그러면 커널 쪽의 eBPF 코드가 맵에서 이 규칙을 읽어와서
enforce something.
무언가를 실행합니다.
That actually, if you think about communities and network policies enforcement using eBPF,
실제로 커뮤니티와 네트워크 정책 시행에 대해 생각해보면, eBPF를 사용하는 것이 좋습니다,
in a nutshell, that's how it works.
간단히 말해서 이렇게 작동합니다.
And now this is very much simplifying a lot.
이제 이것은 매우 단순화되었습니다.
But yeah, you have a process.
하지만 네, 프로세스가 있죠.
They're going to watch for communities policies.
그들은 커뮤니티 정책을 지켜볼 거야.
It's going to transform it into data that can be pushed into a BPF map.
이를 BPF 맵에 푸시할 수 있는 데이터로 변환할 것입니다.
On the other side, you have an eBPF code that reads from this map and enforce the policy.
다른 쪽에는 이 맵을 읽고 정책을 적용하는 eBPF 코드가 있습니다.
So let's do it.
그럼 실행해 봅시다.
Let's see how this would work in communities, or actually in our example here.
이것이 커뮤니티에서 어떻게 작동하는지, 실제로 여기 예제에서 어떻게 작동하는지 살펴봅시다.
So all right, let's keep going here.
그럼 여기서 계속 진행해보죠.
Let's get to our example.
예제를 살펴봅시다.
Click on next.
다음을 클릭합니다.
All right, let's start.
좋아, 시작하자.
So for this example, we're defining a new map.
이 예제에서는 새 맵을 정의하겠습니다.
We're calling that IP rules.
이를 IP 규칙이라고 부릅니다.
It's very straightforward.
아주 간단합니다.
We're actually putting the kind of, you know, a key pair.
우리는 실제로 일종의 키 쌍을 넣고 있습니다.
That's the bit more complicated thing.
그게 좀 더 복잡하죠.
As a key, it's not like a straightforward, like we're not using a direct like an int value
키로서, 우리는 int 값과 같은 다이렉트를 사용하지 않는 것처럼 간단하지 않습니다.
or something.
뭐 그런 거죠.
We're using it in a pair source destination.
페어 소스 대상에서 사용하고 있습니다.
So if we see this source and destination, that's going to be the key.
따라서 이 소스와 목적지를 확인하면 이것이 핵심이 될 것입니다.
The value is going to be a boolean, like just zero or one.
값은 0 또는 1과 같은 부울이 될 것입니다.
And every time we see this key source destination with value zero or one, it will be for us,
그리고 이 키 소스 목적지가 0 또는 1의 값을 가질 때마다 우리를 위한 것이 될 것입니다,
if it's one, allow the traffic.
1이면 트래픽을 허용합니다.
Zero, stop the traffic.
0, 트래픽을 중지합니다.
Very simple.
아주 간단합니다.
So yeah, let's keep going here and let's create our map.
자, 여기서 계속 진행해서 지도를 만들어 봅시다.
Let's take a look at the eBPF code that we just updated.
방금 업데이트한 eBPF 코드를 살펴봅시다.
And let's skip through kind of the first, whatever we talked about when we, you know,
그리고 우리가 처음에 이야기했던 부분은 건너뛰겠습니다,
we talked about monitoring.
모니터링에 대해 얘기했었죠.
Let's focus on security.
보안에 대해 집중해 봅시다.
So we have this section again, it's a key pair source address is going to be the key.
이 섹션은 다시 키 쌍의 소스 주소가 핵심이 될 것입니다.
The value is boolean.
값은 부울입니다.
It just an int is going to be a zero or one.
그냥 0이나 1이 될 것입니다.
Now in modification of our code, scroll all the way down, the same logic we use to write
이제 코드를 수정하여 아래로 스크롤하면 다음과 같은 로직을 작성할 수 있습니다.
in the map, we're going to just read from the map.
지도에서는 그냥 지도를 읽겠습니다.
And we're going to do both.
그리고 둘 다 할 것입니다.
What we're going to do is we're going to say, hey, define a key pair with the source address
우리가 할 일은 소스 주소와 키 쌍을 정의하는 것입니다.
is the source address of the packets.
는 패킷의 소스 주소입니다.
The destination address is the destination address of a certain packets.
목적지 주소는 특정 패킷의 목적지 주소입니다.
So this our key pair, this is our key right now.
이것이 우리의 키 쌍이고, 이것이 지금 우리의 키입니다.
And take a look at the map.
그리고 지도를 보세요.
If you don't see any value, meaning we didn't define any rule, put one, say, hey, well,
어떤 값도 보이지 않는다면, 즉 우리가 어떤 규칙도 정의하지 않았다면, 하나를 입력하세요,
that traffic is allowed, put that in the map, it's fine.
트래픽이 허용된다는 것을 맵에 넣으면 됩니다.
So for us, we can see that from A to B, a certain packet has been allowed.
이제 A에서 B로 특정 패킷이 허용되었음을 알 수 있습니다.
Now if you see explicitly in our map, that the value we defined for this kind of interaction
이제 맵에서 명시적으로 볼 수 있듯이, 이러한 종류의 상호 작용에 대해 정의한 값은 다음과 같습니다.
is zero, then just drop that packet.
가 0이면 해당 패킷을 삭제하면 됩니다.
We don't want it.
원하지 않아요.
All right, let's block that.
좋아, 차단하자.
Amazing.
놀랍군.
That's it.
끝났어요.
That's pretty much what we need to do to define a way to enforce rules between two, like a
둘 사이에 규칙을 적용하는 방법을 정의하려면 다음과 같이 해야 합니다.
source and destination address using eBPF.
소스 및 목적지 주소에 eBPF를 사용합니다.
So let's get back to here.
이제 여기로 돌아가 봅시다.
So we, yeah, so we updated the code.
그래서 코드를 업데이트했습니다.
Let's build this again, the same thing we did earlier.
앞서 했던 것과 똑같이 다시 빌드해 봅시다.
Let's build this again and reload the new code.
다시 빌드하고 새 코드를 다시 로드해 봅시다.
Let's delete the pods.
파드를 삭제하겠습니다.
And wait for them to be ready so we can keep going.
그리고 계속 진행할 수 있도록 준비가 될 때까지 기다리자.
Take a couple seconds here.
여기서 몇 초만 기다려주세요.
Yeah.
알았어
Yeah, I mean, this is a very simple example.
네, 이건 아주 간단한 예시입니다.
But yes, you can define, like you can use the map as hey, well, it's our source of truth
하지만 네, 지도를 다음과 같이 정의할 수 있습니다.
of like what should happen in my network.
내 네트워크에서 어떤 일이 일어나야 하는지
In my example, I'm populating like one saying hey, allow traffic for all the pods.
제 예제에서는 모든 파드에 대한 트래픽을 허용하는 것처럼 채우고 있습니다.
Every time I see like a pair source address, if I don't have an explicit rule, put something
페어 소스 주소와 같은 것을 볼 때마다, 명시적인 규칙이 없다면, 무언가를 넣는다.
in the map saying hey, well, I have one, meaning like I allowed it.
를 맵에 추가하여 내가 허용한 것처럼 보이게 하세요.
But if I explicitly see a zero, then well, that's actually my, but then you can structure,
하지만 내가 명시적으로 0을 본다면, 그건 사실 내 것이지만 구조화할 수 있습니다,
this is an example, you can structure basically your BPF map like you want.
이것은 예시이며, 기본적으로 원하는 대로 BPF 맵을 구조화할 수 있습니다.
You just need to map your logic that you're going to have to do in your packet.
패킷에서 수행해야 할 로직을 매핑하기만 하면 됩니다.
So you do lots of packing and unpacking?
포장과 포장을 푸는 일을 많이 하나요?
The packet doesn't have any performance impact?
패킷이 성능에 영향을 미치지 않나요?
On XDP, very, very minimal, because we're not unpacking.
XDP에서는 압축을 풀지 않기 때문에 매우, 매우 미미합니다.
It's not like we are just, you know, we're just, you know, watching for the structure.
우린 그냥 구조물만 보고 있는 게 아니야.
It's not, we're not modifying the packet itself, right?
패킷 자체를 수정하는 건 아니지?
Like it's mostly, like you can, I mean, you can modify the packet itself.
대부분 패킷 자체를 수정할 수 있는 것처럼요.
But when you just take a look at it, in our case, in this all examples, we didn't do,
하지만 그냥 살펴보면, 이 모든 예제에서 우리는 그렇게 하지 않았습니다,
we didn't rewrite the packets.
패킷을 재작성하지 않았습니다.
We just looked at the packets and made the decision to either monitor that, and in this
우리는 패킷을 살펴보고 이를 모니터링하기로 결정했습니다.
case, we're going to just enforce certain policy.
특정 정책을 시행할 것입니다.
Yes, we are talking about very, very XDP.
네, 우리는 아주 아주 XDP에 대해 이야기하고 있습니다.
It's pretty much, you know, the packet, you don't, you can't see much from it.
거의 패킷에 불과해서 아무것도 볼 수 없습니다.
More you go up, more you can see stuff.
위로 올라갈수록 더 많은 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
So, yeah, let's run a command here.
그럼 여기서 명령을 실행해 봅시다.
Let's make a call and take a look.
전화를 걸어서 살펴봅시다.
Take a look at this map.
이 지도를 보세요.
Now we have a new map that we called IP rules that has source and destination address with
이제 소스 및 목적지 주소가 다음과 같은 IP 규칙이라고 하는 새 맵이 생겼습니다.
certain value.
특정 값입니다.
Basically, we allow traffic from, if you see that split, like, you know, it's kind of the
기본적으로 우리는 트래픽을 허용합니다.
same value, like flipped, but basically a request response.
같은 값이지만 기본적으로 요청 응답입니다.
We sent a request from sleep pod to HTTP bin, it's a one, and from HTTP bin to sleep, when
슬립 파드에서 HTTP 빈으로 요청을 보내면 1이고, HTTP 빈에서 슬립으로 요청을 보내면 다음과 같습니다.
it goes back for the response, it's one, two.
응답을 위해 되돌아가면 1, 2가 됩니다.
So, yes, let's actually look at, now let's look at a user space program that can write
이제 실제로 다음과 같이 작성할 수 있는 사용자 공간 프로그램을 살펴봅시다.
these rules.
이 규칙들을
For that, I wrote something quick for you guys to read.
이를 위해 여러분들이 읽을 수 있도록 간단히 작성했습니다.
We can open the, on the editor, on the user space code.
에디터의 사용자 공간 코드에서 열 수 있습니다.
I already wrote this quickly just for us to save time.
시간 절약을 위해 빠르게 작성했습니다.
What it does is very straightforward.
하는 일은 매우 간단합니다.
It's going to look for the binary of the BDF code that we just wrote and it's going to
방금 작성한 BDF 코드의 바이너리를 찾아서 다음과 같이 실행합니다.
load it, so we're going to skip all this.
로드할 것이므로 이 과정은 생략하겠습니다.
But interesting is it's going to get values from the, kind of, when we call, we invoke
하지만 흥미로운 점은 우리가 호출할 때 일종의
that program with three values.
세 개의 값을 가진 프로그램입니다.
We're going to invoke it with the source address, source IP, a destination IP, and one or zero
소스 주소, 소스 IP, 대상 IP, 그리고 1 또는 0을 사용하여 호출합니다.
to say, hey, allow traffic or not.
트래픽을 허용할지 말지를 알려줍니다.
So, that's it.
이제 끝입니다.
That's all we are doing here.
여기까지입니다.
So, and if we take a look, actually, I already built this for a matter of time.
그래서, 우리가 살펴보면, 사실, 나는 이미 이것을 시간 문제로 만들었습니다.
Take a look at the binary, I already have it.
바이너리를 봐요, 이미 가지고 있어요.
So, again, if we take the, if we test the traffic already, that would work.
다시 말하지만, 우리가 이미 트래픽을 테스트하면 작동할 것입니다.
But now let's actually put an explicit rule to stop the traffic.
하지만 이제 실제로 트래픽을 중지하는 명시적인 규칙을 넣어 봅시다.
For that, I'm using the binary.
이를 위해 바이너리를 사용합니다.
Take a look.
보세요.
You see, IP rule, this is the binary of the user space I created.
보시다시피, IP 규칙, 이것은 제가 만든 사용자 공간의 바이너리입니다.
I'm putting the source address as the IP of the sleep pod.
소스 주소를 슬립 파드의 IP로 설정합니다.
The destination is the IP of HTTP bin pod.
대상은 HTTP 빈 파드의 IP입니다.
And the value I'm putting for the rule is zero, meaning, hey, well, block this traffic.
그리고 규칙에 설정한 값은 0으로, 이 트래픽을 차단하라는 의미입니다.
Let's do this, run it, meaning now in our BPF map, we can take a look at the value.
이제 실행해 보겠습니다. 이제 BPF 맵에서 값을 살펴볼 수 있습니다.
Explicitly, I see a zero here, so don't let this packet go through.
분명히 0이 보이니 이 패킷을 통과시키지 마세요.
And now if I make a call again, voila, blocked.
이제 다시 전화를 걸면 짜잔, 차단되었습니다.
No traffic between A to B.
A와 B 사이에 트래픽이 없습니다.
Okay?
알았지?
This is basically the very simple version of like how we can enforce rules.
이것은 기본적으로 우리가 규칙을 적용하는 방법의 아주 간단한 버전입니다.
Actually, you know what?
사실, 그거 알아요?
As a fun exercise, I just recreated, and you don't do that, okay?
난 그냥 재미삼아 재현한 건데, 넌 그러지 마, 알았지?
That's not how it should be.
그렇게 하면 안 돼요.
I actually created a batch program that just go and parse, here's the batch program.
제가 실제로 그냥 가서 파싱하는 배치 프로그램을 만들었는데, 여기 배치 프로그램이 있습니다.
I created a batch program that goes and basically just watch for Kubernetes network policies.
기본적으로 쿠버네티스 네트워크 정책을 감시하는 배치 프로그램을 만들었습니다.
You would actually use Golang and the client, the kube client for that.
실제로는 골랑과 클라이언트인 큐브 클라이언트를 사용합니다.
Don't use that.
그건 사용하지 마세요.
But in this case, what I'm doing is I'm looking for any network policy,
하지만 이 경우에는 네트워크 정책을 찾고 있습니다,
and I'm actually taking a look at if the source and destination address are allowed,
그리고 실제로 소스 및 대상 주소가 허용되는지 살펴보고 있습니다,
then put an IP rule to allow the traffic.
그런 다음 트래픽을 허용하는 IP 규칙을 넣습니다.
If not, deny all other traffic.
그렇지 않은 경우 다른 모든 트래픽을 거부합니다.
So by default, everything is blocked.
따라서 기본적으로 모든 것이 차단됩니다.
But if I have a kube network policy that is explicitly allowing traffic from A to B,
하지만 A에서 B로의 트래픽을 명시적으로 허용하는 큐브 네트워크 정책을 가지고 있다면,
then allow that, right?
그럼 허용해야겠죠?
It's very simple.
아주 간단합니다.
So if I use this code, I'm going to deploy this here.
이 코드를 사용하면 여기에 배포할 수 있습니다.
Basically, by default, it's blocking all the traffic.
기본적으로 모든 트래픽을 차단하고 있습니다.
There you go.
여기까지입니다.
Now, look, let's create this super basic network policy in Kubernetes.
이제 쿠버네티스에서 이 아주 기본적인 네트워크 정책을 생성해 보자.
We're defining, hey, the matching label, actually, you know, the destination label,
우리는 일치하는 레이블, 즉 대상 레이블을 정의하고 있습니다,
in this case, HTTP bin, and the source address is sleep.
이 경우, HTTP bin이고 소스 주소는 sleep입니다.
So if we execute this code again, which is actually allowing calling from sleep to HTTP bin,
따라서 이 코드를 다시 실행하면 실제로 절전 모드에서 HTTP 빈으로 호출을 허용합니다,
it's not working, right?
작동하지 않죠?
Because by default, I'm blocking all this traffic.
기본적으로 이 모든 트래픽을 차단하고 있기 때문입니다.
But if I go and copy my network policy, create that in Kubernetes,
하지만 내 네트워크 정책을 복사해서 쿠버네티스에 생성하면 된다,
see if that's got created.
생성되었는지 확인한다.
There you go.
됐어요.
It got created on Kubernetes now.
이제 쿠버네티스에서 생성되었다.
My code is running, you know, I'm just doing a loop of like 10 seconds.
내 코드가 실행 중입니다. 10초 정도의 루프를 실행 중입니다.
So it's going to go.
그럼 실행됩니다.
There you go.
됐어요.
It detected the kube policy.
큐브 정책을 감지했습니다.
It's allowing traffic now from the pod that is ending with 200 and the pod that's ending with 15,
이제 200으로 끝나는 파드와 15로 끝나는 파드의 트래픽을 허용한다,
which is the sleep pod and the HTTP bin pod.
이는 슬립 파드와 HTTP 빈 파드이다.
And if I run the code again, there you go.
코드를 다시 실행하면 다음과 같습니다.
We just created a very tiny, tiny, tiny, silly, all right?
방금 아주 작고, 아주 작고, 아주 작고, 아주 바보 같은 것을 만들었어, 알겠어?
Let's basically take a Kubernetes policy, create, you know, write a value in a map,
기본적으로 쿠버네티스 정책을 가져와서 맵에 값을 작성해 봅시다,
get an EBPF code that's been attached with a CNI to enforce a certain security rule.
특정 보안 규칙을 적용하기 위해 CNI와 함께 첨부된 EBPF 코드를 가져온다.
And with that being said, this is the end of this workshop.
이것으로 이 워크샵은 끝입니다.
I hope you guys enjoyed it.
다들 즐거웠길 바랍니다.
There's much things to talk about.
할 얘기가 많네요.
All right, thank you.
알았어, 고마워.
Again, don't recreate that.
다시 말하지만, 다시 만들지 마세요.
I want you, after this session, to be able to open the hood of a car and saying this is the battery
이 세션이 끝나면 자동차 보닛을 열어서 이게 배터리라고 말할 수 있기를 바랍니다.
and this is the engine.
이건 엔진이고요.
And you've opened like, you know, your Kubernetes cluster and look at things like, hey,
그리고 쿠버네티스 클러스터를 열면 다음과 같은 것을 볼 수 있습니다,
well, this is probably a map and this is how things are enforced, okay?
이게 아마 지도일 것이고, 이게 어떻게 적용되는지 알겠죠?
Yeah.
그래
Yes.
Okay, great question.
좋아, 좋은 질문이야.
The question is, is C the only language we can use to write this program?
문제는 이 프로그램을 작성하는 데 사용할 수 있는 언어가 C뿐이냐는 것입니다.
Unfortunately, on the kernel side, it's C.
불행히도 커널 쪽에서는 C입니다.
You're going to have to write your code in C.
코드를 C로 작성해야 합니다.
On the kernel side, for the user space, then you have more flexibility.
커널 쪽에서는 사용자 공간에 대해 더 많은 유연성이 있습니다.
Again, I was going to show you actually this cool project.
다시 한 번, 이 멋진 프로젝트를 보여드리려고 합니다.
If you take a look at the Selium, you know, the Selium EPPF repository,
셀리움을 보시면 아시겠지만, 셀리움 EPPF 저장소가 있습니다,
it has a good example about how to actually load a certain example, like K-probe, for example.
예를 들어 K-probe와 같은 특정 예제를 실제로 로드하는 방법에 대한 좋은 예제가 있습니다.
K-probe will have the backend code and you're going to have some, you know, let's say, user space code.
K-프로브에는 백엔드 코드가 있고, 여러분은 사용자 공간 코드가 있을 것입니다.
Lib eppf2, Rust can be an option.
라이브러리 eppf2, 러스트는 옵션이 될 수 있습니다.
There are certain technologies that now is kind of doing working on what we call binding, right, on the user space.
현재 사용자 공간에서 바인딩이라고 부르는 작업을 하는 특정 기술이 있습니다.
But the backend, it's still going to be C, like a kernel.
하지만 백엔드는 여전히 커널처럼 C로 되어 있습니다.
Yeah.
그렇군요.
Yes, a Rust on the user space.
예, 사용자 공간에 녹이 있습니다.
I mean, I'm pretty sure that's not something that I'm 100% sure that, you know, let's take a look at lib eppf, actually.
제 말은, 제가 100% 확신할 수 있는 것은 아닌 것 같은데, 실제로 lib eppf를 살펴봅시다.
Look, if you go to BPF, BPF bootstrap, it has good examples.
BPF, BPF 부트스트랩에 가보면 좋은 예제가 있습니다.
If you go example here, you can take a look, there's a Rust repo to give you a couple things.
여기 예제를 보시면 몇 가지를 알려주는 Rust 저장소가 있습니다.
Let's take a look at XDP.
XDP를 살펴봅시다.
So, yeah.
그러네요.
Actually, BPF, now I think the BPF itself was written in C, right?
사실, BPF, 이제 BPF 자체가 C로 작성된 것 같지 않나요?
But I think the loading was in Rust.
하지만 로딩은 Rust로 된 것 같아요.
I think that's where it is.
거기 있는 것 같아요.
In the kernel space, do you have to worry about normal concurrency constructs and stuff like that?
커널 공간에서 일반적인 동시성 구조나 그런 것들에 대해 걱정할 필요가 있나요?
Because when you're doing the incrementing, there's...
왜냐하면 증분을 할 때...
Yeah, I mean, you should probably...
네, 제 말은, 아마...
I didn't very much double talk too much on the BPF map.
BPF 맵에서 너무 이중적인 말을 많이 하지 않았어.
There's BPF maps that are very much isolated by CPU and so on.
CPU 등에 의해 매우 고립된 BPF 맵이 있습니다.
So you can define, you know, when you're writing any resource, obviously, concurrency is a...
그래서 어떤 리소스를 작성할 때, 분명히 동시성을 정의할 수 있습니다.
It may be a problem.
문제가 될 수 있습니다.
But most of the time, you just need to design the right thing.
하지만 대부분의 경우 제대로 설계하기만 하면 됩니다.
So if you're writing a map, just try to figure out the right use case for you.
따라서 지도를 작성할 때는 자신에게 맞는 사용 사례를 찾아보세요.
If something that is very much segregated for a node, for example, to limit the interaction between multiple users, it can be an option.
예를 들어 여러 사용자 간의 상호 작용을 제한하기 위해 노드에 대해 매우 분리된 무언가가 있다면, 그것은 옵션이 될 수 있습니다.
But yeah, I think that's something that you still have to worry about.
하지만 네, 그건 여전히 걱정해야 할 부분이라고 생각합니다.
But if you look at libBPF and look at a lot of projects, there's a lot of...
하지만 libBPF를 보고 많은 프로젝트를 보면, 많은...
It's emerging. There's a lot of new code, new technology that kind of simplifies life for you.
떠오르고 있습니다. 새로운 코드, 새로운 기술이 많이 등장해서 삶을 단순화시켜주고 있습니다.
Like when you write a specific code, I didn't talk about it much, but eBPF is very strict, very strict.
특정 코드를 작성할 때처럼, 제가 많이 이야기하지는 않았지만 eBPF는 매우 엄격하고 매우 엄격합니다.
You cannot just go and create any C code.
아무 코드나 아무렇게나 만들 수 없습니다.
Once it detects that you are going to write something out of range or do something that it should not be doing, it's not going to allow you to even build it.
범위를 벗어난 코드를 작성하거나 해서는 안 되는 일을 하려는 것을 감지하면 빌드조차 허용하지 않습니다.
Or if it builds it, it doesn't allow you to mount it.
또는 빌드하더라도 마운트할 수 없습니다.
So I think you have a lot of controls there.
그래서 거기에 많은 컨트롤이 있는 것 같아요.
And if you look at the BPF code, look at the BPF tools, it helps you answer these questions you have.
그리고 BPF 코드를 보면, BPF 도구를 보면 이런 질문에 답하는 데 도움이 됩니다.
Any other questions?
다른 질문이 있나요?
Is there a way to see what BPF code has been noted?
어떤 BPF 코드가 기록되었는지 확인할 수 있는 방법이 있나요?
Like if I was on the server and you wrote some block home, both RAM and then went home.
예를 들어 제가 서버에 있을 때 어떤 블록을 램과 램 모두에 쓴 다음 집으로 돌아갔다면요.
Is there a way to break BPF code?
BPF 코드를 깨는 방법이 있나요?
To know that actually this BPF code got bit invoked? Is that what you're saying?
실제로 이 BPF 코드가 호출되었다는 것을 알고 싶으신가요? 그런 뜻인가요?
Yeah, so you saw what we did with IP rules.
네, 우리가 IP 규칙으로 뭘 했는지 보셨죠?
We set like zero and like if the rule got blocked, it's like a one or something.
0으로 설정하고 규칙이 차단되면 1로 설정하는 식으로요.
That's how you should design probably your eBPF code.
이것이 아마도 여러분의 eBPF 코드를 설계하는 방법일 것입니다.
You should actually think about, okay, I'm going to define the rule.
실제로 규칙을 정의해야 합니다.
The rule for me is to block A to B, but also I need to define the monitoring aspect.
내 규칙은 A에서 B로 차단하는 것이지만 모니터링 측면도 정의해야 합니다.
And let's define the, let's say you can create a metric like we did earlier to say every time I'm blocking from A to B because of my code, go create this metric that you can go and put that in Prometheus and alert on it.
그리고 앞서 했던 것처럼 내 코드 때문에 A에서 B로 차단할 때마다 이 메트릭을 만들어서 Prometheus에 넣고 알림을 보낼 수 있는 메트릭을 만들 수 있다고 가정해 봅시다.
Again, when you create your eBPF code, think about the monitoring aspect and also the enforcement aspect.
다시 한 번 강조하지만, eBPF 코드를 만들 때는 모니터링 측면과 실행 측면을 모두 고려하세요.
Maybe you're asking about the delivery that already comes from the computer or not.
컴퓨터에서 이미 전달된 배달에 대해 묻는 것일 수도 있습니다.
Oh, so you're saying, can we take a look if a certain, okay, so if you use like, in my example, I'm using BPF tool, right?
아, 그러니까 특정, 그러니까 예를 들어 제 예제에서는 BPF 도구를 사용하는지 살펴볼 수 있느냐는 말씀이시죠?
BPF tool is pretty cool and you can use different things.
BPF 도구는 꽤 멋지고 다양한 것을 사용할 수 있습니다.
You can use BPF cool, BPF cool, that's a good name.
BPF 멋지다, BPF 멋지다, 좋은 이름이야.
BPF tool on a certain interface is going to list all the eBPF code that's been attached to this interface.
특정 인터페이스의 BPF 도구는 이 인터페이스에 첨부된 모든 eBPF 코드를 나열합니다.
So you can always go back and say, oh, well, like what this kind of actually thing is not working.
그래서 언제든 돌아가서 이런 것이 실제로 작동하지 않는다고 말할 수 있습니다.
Oh, like let's run BPF tool on a certain interface.
아, 특정 인터페이스에서 BPF 도구를 실행해 봅시다.
Okay, well, all these things are being attached.
좋아, 이 모든 것들이 연결되고 있네요.
Therefore, this is why it's enforced.
따라서 이것이 시행되는 이유입니다.
Network interface, correct.
네트워크 인터페이스, 맞습니다.
Yeah, yeah, eBPF is definitely, again, we are just seeing that in the context of networking.
네, 네, 네, eBPF는 확실히 네트워킹의 맥락에서 볼 수 있습니다.
But eBPF code can be running for, let's say, SIS calls or like system calls or opening a file here, you know, things that are in, you know, let's say you want to monitor other aspects of Linux.
하지만 eBPF 코드는 예를 들어 학생 정보 시스템 호출이나 시스템 호출, 파일 열기 등 리눅스의 다른 측면을 모니터링하고 싶을 때 실행될 수 있습니다.
It doesn't have to be networking.
꼭 네트워킹일 필요는 없습니다.
But obviously, interface comes in discussion when we're talking about networking for sure.
하지만 분명히 네트워킹에 대해 이야기할 때 인터페이스가 논의되는 것은 당연합니다.
Okay, thank you very much for joining this session. Hope to see you soon and have a good KubeCon.
좋아요, 이 세션에 참여해 주셔서 대단히 감사합니다. 곧 다시 뵙고 즐거운 KubeCon이 되길 바랍니다.